-肯特  -伯爵
-Kent. -My lord.
走这边
Come on.
我原本以为奥本尼公爵会比康华尔公爵更被王上看中
I thought the king had more affected the Duke of Albany than Cornwall.
我们倒是一向都这么认为 但在这次的国土分割中
It did always seem so to us, but now in the division of the kingdom
却看不出他更加青睐谁
it appears not which of the dukes he values most,
这次分配如此平均
for qualities are so weighed
两位公爵再斤斤计较 都没法说对方比自己受益更多
that curiosity in neither can make choice of either's moiety.
公爵 这是令郎吗
Is not this your son, my lord?
实话告诉您 他的出生我要负全责
His breeding, sir, hath been at my charge.
我过去经常面红耳赤地承认他是我的儿子 但现在我已经释然了
I've so often blushed to acknowledge him that now I am brazed to it.
我不太明白您的意思
I cannot conceive you.
这个小伙子的妈妈可以让您搞清楚是怎么回事
Sir, this young fellow's mother could.
虽然这个混小子自作主张地来到人世
Though this knave came something saucily into the world,
却不得不说生下他的那个女人是个尤物
我们在制造他的时候曾经有过一场刺激的游戏
there was good sport at his making and the whoreson must be acknowledged.
-埃德蒙 你认识这位大人吗 -不认识 公爵
-Do you know this noble gentleman, Edmund? -No, my lord.
他是肯特公爵  从此刻起你应当时牢牢记住他是我尊贵的友人
My Lord of Kent. Remember him hereafter as my honourable friend.
他在国外待了九年 不久之后还会再次出去
He has been out nine years and away he shall again.
国王驾到
The king is coming.
葛罗斯特 你去接待一下法兰西国王和勃艮第伯爵
Attend the Lords of France and Burgundy, Gloucester.
是  陛下
Ay, my good lord.
与此同时 我要和你们说说我心中那见不得光的计划
Meantime we shall express our darker purpose.
把那份地图拿给我
Give me the map there.
告诉你们 国土已经被我划分成了三份
Know that we have divided in three our kingdom.
我年岁也不小了 该要快些卸下身上的担子才是
'Tis our fast intent to shake all cares and business from our age,
把这些事情交给年轻一辈来做
conferring them on younger strengths,
这样才好一身轻松地慢慢走向死亡
while we unburdened crawl toward death.
康华尔伯爵 还有你 荣宠不比他少的奥本尼公爵 我的两位好女婿
Our son of Cornwall, and you, our no less loving son of Albany,
我想此时我应该公布我的女儿们到底有多少嫁妆
we have this hour a constant will to publish our daughters' several dowers,
以防日后发生争执
that future strife may be prevented now.
法兰西的王子和勃艮第公爵为了得到我小女儿的垂青正争得火热
The princes France and Burgundy, great rivals in our youngest daughter's love,
他们已经怀揣着热情似火的心在我这里住了有些时日了
long in our court have made their amorous sojourn,
他们现在该得到答复了
and here are to be answered.
告诉我吧 女儿们
Tell me, my daughters,
值此之际 我即将放弃我的统治 我的领土 和诸多国事
since now we will divest us both of rule, interest of territory, cares of state,
让我来听听 你们之中哪一个最爱我
which of you shall we say doth love us most,
让我们看看谁对我有与生俱来的爱 看看谁将因此得到最高的奖赏
that we our largest bounty may extend where nature doth with merit challenge?
戈纳瑞 你是老大 你先说
Goneril, our eldest born, speak first.
父亲……
Sir...
我对您的爱 再多的言语都不够表达
I love you more than words can wield the matter.
我珍视您胜过我的双眼 热爱您胜过爱这大千世界
对您的向往 更甚于我对自由的追求
Dearer than eyesight, space, and liberty,
超越一切可以估价的贵重稀有的事物
beyond what can be valued, rich or rare,
更不亚于对一个拥有恩惠 财富 健康 美貌和荣誉的生命的渴求
no less than life, with grace, health, beauty, honour,
没有哪个孩子如此爱她的父亲 也从未有过哪个父亲 被女儿这样深爱
as much as child e'er loved, or father found,
这种爱让唇舌无力 言语在它面前都失去了意义
a love that makes breath poor and speech unable.
我爱您 超越了一切可以表达爱的方式 我爱您
Beyond all manner of so much I love you.
在我国土的这些疆界以内
Of all these bounds,
从这条线起 一直到这一条为止 这其中所有茂密的森林 肥沃的平原
even from this line to this, with shadowy forests and with champains riched,
丰盈的河流 和广袤的牧场
with plenteous rivers and wide-skirted meads,
你就是他们的女主人了
we make thee lady.
这块土地是你和奥本尼的 也将被你们的子孙世世代代所拥有
To thine and Albany's issue be this perpetual.
来听听我的二女儿 亲爱的里根 康华尔的夫人 是怎么说的
What says our second daughter, our dearest Regan, wife to Cornwall?
来吧
Speak.
呃……我和我的姐姐有着相似的品质 您凭着她 就能得出对我的判断
Er... I am made of that self mettle as my sister, and prize me at her worth.
我真诚地觉得 姐姐刚才的一番话 将我对你那不可名状的爱具像化了
In my true heart, I find she names my very deed of love.
只可惜姐姐说的话还不足以完全表达我对您的爱
Only she comes too short:
我厌弃这世上所有
that I profess myself an enemy to all other joys
凡是敏锐知觉能感受到的愉悦和快乐
which the most precious square of sense possesses,
只有沐浴在您无上的荣宠里 我才真的开心和幸福
and find I am alone felicitate in your dear highness' love.
那么你和你的子孙将会世代继承
And to thee and thine hereditary ever
这块从我们伟大王国的国土中 划分出来的三分之一的肥沃土地
remain this ample third of our fair kingdom,
你的土地和我刚划分给戈纳瑞的同样广阔 同样肥沃 一点儿不比她差
no less in space, validity and pleasure than that conferred on Goneril.
现在该轮到我的小宝贝儿了 虽然是最后一个发言 但也一样我心尖儿上的女儿
Now our joy, although the last and least,
那法兰西的葡萄和勃艮第的牛奶
to whose young love the vines of France and milk of Burgundy
都想得到你那充满青春活力的爱情
strive to be interessed.
你有什么要说的话 可以为你赢得比你两个姐姐更为富饶的土地呢
What can you say to draw a third more opulent than your sisters?
说吧
Speak.
父亲 我没话说
Nothing, my lord.
-没有话要说     -没有
-Nothing?  -Nothing.
但不说话你就什么都换不到了 （给你个机会 好好想想）重新再说一次吧
Well, nothing will come of nothing. Speak again.
我很难过 因为我没办法把我的心意送到嘴边
Unhappy that I am, I cannot heave my heart into my mouth.
我对陛下的爱 谨遵您赐予我的名分 一分不多 一分不少
I love your majesty according to my bond, no more nor less.
怎么这样说话 考狄利娅 把你的话修正一下 否则你将毁掉你的命运
How now, Cordelia? Mend your speech a little, lest you may mar your fortunes.
是 父亲 您赐予我生命 养育我 疼爱我
Ay, my good lord, you have begot me, bred me, loved me.
为了报答您 我会履行我的责任：
I return those duties back as are right fit:
顺从您 爱您 敬重您
obey you, love you, and most honour you.
如果姐姐们真像她们所说的那样爱您 她们为什么要嫁给别人呢
Why have my sisters husbands if they say they love you all?
我绝对不会像姐姐们一样嫁给别人 我要用全部的身心来爱您 我的父亲
Sure I shall never marry like my sisters to love my father all.
你说这些都是真心话吗
But goes thy heart with this?
句句真心 父亲
Ay, my good lord.
你年纪这么小 怎会如此没有良心
So young, and so untender?
父亲 我年纪小 但我有一颗赤诚的真心
So young, my lord, and true.
那我就成全你的真心 你就用你那高贵的真诚当作嫁妆吧
Let it be so. Thy truth then be thy dower.
我发誓从现在起 你我再无半点关系 不是父女 不是亲人
Here I disclaim all my paternal care,
从此你在我心里只是一个毫不相干的旁人 我这辈子都不会改变心意了
and as a stranger to my heart and me hold thee from this for ever.
-陛下……-闭嘴 肯特
-Good my liege... -Peace, Kent!
不要触碰我的逆鳞
Come not between the dragon and his wrath.
我爱她最深 我还曾想在她的细心照顾下 颐养天年
I loved her most, and thought to set my rest on her kind nursery.
走开 别再让我看到你
Hence, and avoid my sight!
把法兰西王叫来 怎么一个个都不动 把勃艮第也叫来
Call France. Who stirs? Call Burgundy!
哈哈
Ha, ha!
康华尔和奥本尼
你们俩已经得到了我两个女儿的嫁妆 现在把这第三份也拿去分了吧
Cornwall and Albany, with my two daughters' dowers digest the third.
（至于考狄利娅） 就让她那所谓的坦诚 为她找一个丈夫吧
我两位杰出而优秀的女儿们 我把我的权利
I do invest you jointly with my power, pre-eminence,
我的影响力 连同作为君主的权威 一起交给你们
and all the large effects that troop with majesty.
而我 我只为自己保留……
Ourself by monthly course, with reservation of...
一百名骑士 由你们来供养我
an hundred knights, by you to be sustained,
我将每个月轮流到你们的领地去居住
shall our abode make with you by due turn.
我只给自己留下国王的名义和各种尊号头衔
Only we still retain the name and all the addition to a king.
所有的统治权 财政大权 处理大小事务的权力 两位贤婿 我把它交给你们
The sway, revenue, execution of the rest, beloved sons, be yours.
李尔陛下 我一向敬您为我的君王
Royal Lear, whom I have ever honoured as my king,
奉您为我的伟大保护神……
as my great patron thought on in my prayers...
箭已然在弦上 弓已经被拉满 你就留心怎么躲开箭锋吧
The bow is bent and drawn, make from the shaft.
那就尽管让它射过来吧 就算箭镞会戳进我的心脏
Let it fall rather, though the fork invade the region of my heart.
既然您已经失去理智了 我也只好失礼了
Be Kent unmannerly when Lear is mad?
你到底想怎样 老头
What wouldst thou do, old man?
你以为当权威被谄媚者夺走时 尽忠职守的人就不敢说话了吗
Thinkest thou that duty shall have dread to speak when power to flattery bows?
肯特 住嘴 你还想不想保命了
Kent, on thy life, no more!
我的生命原本是向你仇敌抛掷的武器
My life I never held but as a pawn to wage against thine enemies.
-走开 -先生 冷静一点……
-Out of my sight! -Dear sir, forbear...
-好好把事情看清楚些 李尔 -现在 以太阳神阿波罗起誓……
-See better, Lear! -Now, by Apollo...
哦我的国王 现在你以阿波罗的名义起誓
Oh, now, by Apollo, king.
你向神神明发誓也没用 我告诉你 你是个恶魔
Thou swear'st thy gods in vain. I'll tell thee, thou dost evil.
听着 懦夫
Hear me, recreant.
怀着你对我的忠诚给我听好了
On thine allegiance, hear me!
你妄想怂恿我违背我刚发过的誓言 这是我们从来都不敢做的
That thou hast sought to make us break our vows, which we durst never yet,
为了维护我王权的尊严 你将接受应得的惩罚
our potency made good, take thy reward.
我给你五天时间 让你准备些衣服和食物
Five days we do allot thee, for provision
免得你饱受这世上饥饿和寒冷或者疾病的痛苦
to shield thee from diseases of the world,
第六天 你那可憎的身体必须离开我的国土
and on the sixth to turn thy hated back upon our kingdom.
如果在此后的十天之内
If, on the tenth day following,
在我的领土上发现了你的踪迹 那就是你的死期
thy banished trunk be found in our dominions, the moment is thy death.
走吧 以丘比特之神的名义
Away, by Jupiter.
这个决定是绝对不可更改的
This shall not be revoked!
我尊贵的陛下 法兰西王和勃艮第来了
Here's France and Burgundy, my noble lord!
尊敬的陛下
My noble lord.
勃艮第公爵
My Lord of Burgundy,
我先来和你说说 你和法兰西国王都在争夺我的女儿
we first address towards you, who with this king hath rivalled for our daughter.
你希望她至少要有多少陪嫁的奁资
What in the least will you require in present dower with her
否则你宁愿舍弃你对她的爱
or cease your quest of love?
我尊贵的陛下 您提出的数目我就已经很满足了 不会再奢求更多
Most royal majesty, I crave no more than hath your highness offered,
想来您也不会吝啬的 陛下
nor will you tender less.
尊贵的勃艮第 当我还十分宠爱她时 她对我来说是十分珍贵的
Right noble Burgundy, when she was dear to us, we did hold her so.
但现在她已经掉价了
But now her price is fallen.
先生 你看她 就站在那儿 看起来那么小一个东西
Sir, there she stands. If aught within that little seeming substance,
要是我能给她的只有憎恨
or all of it, with our displeasure pieced,
再没有别的了 如果这样了你还是喜欢她
and nothing more, may fitly like your grace,
她就在那儿 她就属于你了
she's there, and she is yours.
我不知道该怎么回答您
I know no answer.
像她这样一个软弱无能 无亲无故 又才遭受我的憎恨的女孩儿
Will you with those infirmities she owes, unfriended, new-adopted to our hate,
我的诅咒就是她的嫁妆 而且我已立誓和她断绝关系了
dowered with our curse and strangered with our oath,
-你愿意娶她吗 还是就此放弃  -请您宽恕 陛下
-take her or leave her? -Pardon me, royal sir.
在这样的情况下 我是很难抉择的
Election makes not up in such conditions.
那就放弃她把 公爵
就凭着赐予我生命的神灵起誓 我已经告诉你了她的全部价值
Then leave her, sir, for by the power that made me I tell you all her wealth.
至于你 伟大的国王
For you, great king,
为了你我珍贵的友谊 我是万不会讲一个我如此憎恶的人许配给你的
I would not from your love make such a stray to match you where I hate.
陛下 我恳请您让世人明白
I yet beseech your majesty that you make it known
不是罪恶的污点、谋杀 或是卑鄙的行为
it is no vicious blot, murder, or foulness,
也不是不贞洁或不光彩的做法
no unchaste action or dishonoured step
让我一下子就失去了您的厚爱
that hath deprived me of your grace and favour.
你最好从没来到过这世上……
Better thou hadst not been born...
总比像今天这样惹恼我要好得多
than not to have pleased me better.
尊敬的勃艮第伯爵 你对她意下如何呢 你会娶她吗
My Lord of Burgundy, what say you to the lady? Will you have her?
只要您给我之前所允诺的那份嫁妆
Give but that portion which yourself proposed,
我就可以让她成为勃艮第公爵夫人
and I will make Cordelia Duchess of Burgundy.
我什么都不能给你了 我已经发过誓 我绝不会违背誓言
Nothing. I have sworn, I am firm.
这样的话 我只能说很抱歉了
I am sorry, then.
你已经失去了一个父亲 现在又得失去一个丈夫了
You have so... lost a father that you must lose a husband.
愿和平伴随着勃艮第国土
Peace be with Burgundy.
既然名望和财富才是他心中所爱 那我也不能作他的妻子
Since that respect and fortunes are his love, I shall not be his wife.
最美丽的考狄利娅
Fairest Cordelia,
现在我将她连同她的美德一起握在手里
thee and thy virtues here I seize upon.
那你把她带走吧 法兰西王
Thou hast her, king.
让她成为你的妻子
Let her be thine,
我没有这样的女儿 以后也不会想再见到她了
for we have no such daughter, nor shall ever see that face of hers again.
那么你们去吧 你们不需要我的恩惠 我的爱
Therefore be gone, without our grace, our love,
我的祝福
our benison.
跟我走
Come!
和你的姐姐们好好道别吧
Bid farewell to your sisters.
好好爱戴我们的父亲
Love well our father.
用不着你来说我们该做什么
Prescribe not us our duty.
你还是好好费心该怎么侍奉你的丈夫吧 慈悲的命运把你交付到他手里
Let your study be to content your lord, who hath received you at fortune's alms.
我觉得我们的父亲今晚就会离开
I think our father will hence tonight.
那是肯定的 他会先和你住在一块儿 下个月到我们那儿
That's most certain, and with you. Next month with us.
你也看见了 他上了年纪 脾气更加变幻莫测 他向来最疼爱我们的妹妹
You see how full of changes his age is. He always loved our sister most
今天居然一气之下想也不想把她撵走 可见他已经是多么糊涂了
and with what poor judgement he hath now cast her off appears too grossly.
年纪大了难免会这样 可他一直以来都是这么喜怒不定的
'Tis the infirmity of his age, yet he hath ever but slenderly known himself.
他还是健康的青壮年时 脾气就暴躁鲁莽的很
The best and soundest of his time hath been but rash.
如果我们的父亲惯着自己的脾气滥用权威 这一次划分国土的事情
If our father carry authority with such disposition as this,
说不定什么时候反倒会让我们遭殃
it will but offend us.
-我们得对此作长远打算 -我们必须得趁热打铁做点儿什么
-We shall further think on it. -We must do something, and i' the heat.
祈祷吧 这次让我们姐妹同心
Pray, let us hit together.
你 大自然 是我的女神啊
Thou, Nature, art my goddess.
我愿受你的法律约束
To thy law my services are bound.
为什么我是私生子
Why bastard?
为什么我比别人卑贱 明明我的各个方面都和他们没有差别
Wherefore base, when my dimensions are as well compact,
我慷慨的精神 庄健的体格 端正的容貌 哪一点比不上正经女人生的孩子
my mind as generous and my shape as true as honest madam's issue?
为什么他们要给我贴上卑贱的标签
Why brand they me with base?
为什么要说我是贱种 是私生子
With baseness? Bastardy?
合法的哥哥 埃德伽 我一定要得到你的土地
Legitimate Edgar, I must have your land.
我合法的哥哥
Well, my legiti-mate,
我 爱德蒙 这个私生子 有朝一日会把你压在脚下
Edmund the base shall top the legitimate.
不好意思 失陪一下
Excuse me.
埃德蒙 怎么了 有什么新消息吗
Edmund, how now? What news?
父亲 我不知道有什么新闻啊
I know no news, my lord.
-你手上读的那封信是什么 -没什么 父亲
-What paper were you reading? -Nothing, my lord.
什么都没有
No?
要是没什么的话 你为何要慌慌张张把它塞进你的衣袋
What needed then that terrible dispatch of it into your pocket?
要是上面真的没有什么的话 它根本就不必被藏起来
The quality of nothing hath not such need to hide itself.
来 拿出来给我看看吧 要是上面没有什么的话我也不需要戴眼镜了
Let's see. Come, if it be nothing I shall not need spectacles.
我恳求您 父亲 请您原谅我
I beseech you, sir, pardon me.
这是哥哥写给我的信 但我还没有读完
It is a letter from my brother that I have not all o'er-read,
从我已经读到的内容看 我觉得你还是不要读的好
and for so much as I have perused, I find it not fit for your o'erlooking.
小伙子 把信给我
Give me the letter, sir.
唉……
Hmm...
“要是我们的父亲在我把他叫醒之前一直好好睡着
"If our father would sleep till I waked him,
你就可以一直享有他一半的收入
you should enjoy half his revenue for ever
并且生活在你哥哥我的疼爱之中 埃德伽”
and live the beloved of your brother. Edgar."
“在我把他叫醒之前一直好好睡着……享受他一半的收入 ”我的儿子埃德伽
"Sleep till I waked him... Enjoy half his revenue." My son Edgar?
-这封信是什么时候到你手里的 谁把信带给你的  -我在我的房间里发现的
-When came you to this? Who brought it? -I found it in my room.
你认得这是你哥哥的笔迹
You know the character to be your brother's?
要是信中所言都是些好东西 父亲 我敢发誓是他的笔迹
If the matter were good, my lord, I durst swear it were his,
但鉴于信上写的是这种话 我倒宁愿不是他写的
but in respect of that, I would fain think it were not.
-可这就是他的笔迹  -这个的确是他的笔迹 父亲
-It is his. -It is his hand, my lord,
但我希望他说这些话的时候心里并没有真的这么想
but I hope his heart is not in the contents.
他以前从没有用这类似的话试探过你
Has he never before sounded you in this business?
从没有 父亲 可我常常听他提起
Never, my lord, but I have heard him oft maintain it to be fit
儿子成年以后父亲也已经衰老了
that, sons at perfect age and fathers declined,
于是父亲应该受到儿子的监视 让儿子来管理他的财产
the father should be as ward to the son and the son manage his revenue.
哦 真是个混蛋
O villain!
混蛋 他在信里说的就是这个意思
Villain. His very opinion in the letter.
-去把他给我找来 他在哪儿 -我不是很清楚 父亲
-Go seek him. Where is he? -I do not well know, my lord.
最近出现的这些日食月食果然不是什么好兆头
These late eclipses of the sun and moon portend no good to us.
我们的好日子已经不复返了
We have seen the best of our time.
找到这个混蛋 埃德蒙
Find out this villain, Edmund.
这对你也没什么不好的
It shall lose thee nothing.
行动的时候小心些
Do it carefully.
人们最爱用这种华而不实的想法蒙骗自己
This is the excellent foppery of the world,
当我们应为自己不当的行为而遭遇不测时
that when we are sick in fortune, often the surfeits of our own behaviour,
我们将自己受到的灾祸归因于日月星辰
we make guilty of our disasters the sun, the moon, and stars,
就好像我们成为罪人是命中注定 成为傻瓜也是上天的旨意
as if we were villains of necessity, fools by heavenly compulsion,
人们变成无赖 小偷 叛国贼 好像都有一颗星球在背后操纵
knaves, thieves and treasoners by spherical predominance,
酗酒 造谣
drunkards, liars,
通奸 好像大家是被迫受到了行星的影响
and adulterers by an enforced obedience of planetary influence,
无论我们犯下什么罪恶的行径
都好像是因为有一种神秘的力量在背后主导着一切
and all that we are evil in by a divine thrusting on.
一切如何啊 我的弟弟埃德蒙
How now, brother Edmund?
这些日食月食果然预示着纷争与决裂
O these eclipses do portend these divisions.
你又在思考什么严肃的事情啊
What serious contemplation are you in?
我在想 哥哥 关于我最近读到的一个预言
I am thinking, brother, of a prediction I read this other day.
说的是 这些日食月食之后 将会发生什么
What should follow these eclipses.
你就让这些东西困扰着你吗
Do you busy yourself with that?
我向你保证 他一语成谶
I promise you, the effects he writes of succeed unhappily.
你最近一次看见父亲是什么时候
When saw you my father last?
呃……昨天晚上
Er... The night gone by.
你和他说过话没有
Spake you with him?
说了 我和他交谈了两个小时
Ay. Two hours together.
你没有在他的言辞表情之间感受到一点恼怒吗
Found you no displeasure in him by word nor countenance?
一点儿也没有
None at all.
想想看你是不是在什么地方得罪了他
Bethink yourself wherein you may have offended him,
听我的劝 暂时避开他一下
and at my entreaty forbear his presence
等他的怒气稍微平息一点再说
until some little time hath qualified the heat of his displeasure,
他现在正在气头上
which at this instant so rageth in him
说不定会对你造成什么伤害呢
that with the mischief of your person it would scarcely allay.
-一定是有哪个坏东西在背后诋毁我 -这也是我所忧虑的
-Some villain hath done me wrong. -No, that's my fear.
我现在还是想请你和我到我住的地方去
I pray you retire with me to my lodging,
我可以想法子让你藏起来 听听他老人家怎么说
from whence I will fitly bring you to hear my lord speak.
算我求你了 快走吧
Pray ye, go.
这是我的钥匙 你要是在外面走动的话 最好带些武器
There's my key. If you do stir abroad, go armed.
武器 弟弟……
Armed? Brother...
哥哥 我劝你最好这么做
Brother, I advise you to the best.
我已经把听到看到的都告诉你了 但我说的也只是轻描淡写
I have told you what I have seen and heard but faintly,
实际情况比我说的严重多了
nothing like the image and horror of it.
求你了 快走吧
-Pray you, away. -
一个轻信谗言的父亲 和一个高贵的哥哥
A credulous father and a brother noble,
他如此善良的本性使得他不会怀疑任何人
whose nature is so far from doing harms that he suspects none.
我可要扬眉吐气了
I grow, I prosper.
现在 众神帮帮私生子吧
Now, gods, stand up for bastards.
-我能很快从你这里得到消息吗   -一切交给我来办
-Shall I hear from you anon? -I do serve you in this business.
被放逐的肯特
Now, banished Kent,
要是你顶着一身罪名 还依然能够尽忠心
if thou canst serve where thou dost stand condemned,
总有一天 你的主人
so may it come, thy master, whom thou lovest,
会体察到你的功劳
shall find thee full of labours.
不要耽搁 立刻开始晚餐吧
Let me not stay a jot for dinner!
-怎么回事儿 你是谁   -一个人 先生
-How now, what art thou? -A man, sir.
喔 你是做什么的
Oh. What dost thou profess?
你看我像做什么的 我就是做什么的
I do profess to be no less than I seem.
嗯...  你想干嘛   -为您服务
-Hm... What wouldst thou? -Service.
为谁服务   -您
-Who wouldst thou serve? -You.
伙计 你认识我吗   -不认识 先生
-Dost thou know me, fellow? -No, sir.
但是您的神情
But you have that in your countenance
让我有一股愿意为之臣服的气质
which I would fain call master.
那是什么气质
What's that?
-威严  -啊
-Authority. -Ah.
那好 跟着我吧 你可以侍奉我
Well, follow me. Thou shalt serve me.
如果晚饭后 我还是这么喜欢你 我就不会让你走了
If I like thee no worse after dinner, I will not part from thee yet.
晚餐   晚餐
-Dinner ho!  Dinner ho!
Dinner ho! Dinner ho!
晚餐   晚餐   晚餐   晚餐
Dinner ho! Dinner ho! Dinner ho! Dinner ho!
晚餐   晚餐   晚餐   晚餐   晚餐
Dinner ho! Dinner ho! Dinner ho! Dinner ho! Dinner ho!
晚餐   晚餐
Dinner ho! Dinner ho!
晚餐   晚餐  晚餐   晚餐
Dinner ho! Dinner ho! Dinner ho! Dinner ho!
晚餐   晚餐
Dinner ho! Dinner!
我的跟班儿在哪儿呢 我的佣人呢
Where's my knave, my fool? Eh?
进去把我的佣人叫来
Go you and call my fool hither.
你 你 就是你
Ah. You, sir, you.
小子 我的女儿哪里去了
You! Sirrah, where's my daughter?
不好意思
So please you.
那个家伙在说什么  把那个蠢货叫回来
What says the fellow there? Call the clotpoll back.
我的佣人呢?  全都睡着了吗
Where's my fool? I think the world's asleep. Hm.
他从早到晚都要责备我
By day and night he wrongs me.
每个小时他都要挑起新的事端 把我们这里搅得鸡犬不宁
Every hour he flashes into one gross crime or other that sets us all at odds.
-我受不了了
-I'll not endure it.
他的骑士日益横行不法 而且他经常因为一点点小事就责备我们
His knights grow riotous and himself upbraids us on every trifle.
救说我病了
Say I am sick.
你尽管对她摆出一副不理不睬的样子
Put on what weary negligence you please.
他要是恼了 就让他去我妹妹那
If he distaste it, let him to my sister,
我知道他她跟我一样 不愿受到欺压
whose mind and mine I know in that are one, not to be overruled.
好的,夫人
Well, madam.
-怎么回事 那个杂种在哪  -他说你女儿身体不适 陛下
-Where's that mongrel? -He says your daughter is not well.
我喊他过来的时候 那个奴才为什么不过来
Why came not the slave back when I called him?
-大人 他非常放肆的回答我说 他不想过来
Sir, he answered me in the roundest manner he would not.
-他不想
-He would not?   Ooh...
去告诉我的女儿 说我有话要跟她说
Go and tell my daughter I would speak with her.
-你去把我的佣人叫来 -是
-Go you, call hither my fool. -Sir.
啊 是你 你过来
O, you sir, you, come you hither, sir.
知道我是谁吗  先生
Who am I, sir?
-我女主人的父亲 -我女主人的父亲
-My lady's father. -My lady's father?
我们陛下的奴才 你个婊子养的狗东西 你这个奴才 你这个杂种
My lord's knave, you whoreson dog, you slave, you cur.
请您原谅 陛下 我并不是你所说的那些
I am none of these, my lord, I beseech your pardon.
-竟敢跟我瞪眼 你这无赖 -你不能打我 陛下
-Bandy looks with me, rascal? -I'll not be struck, my lord.
也不能绊你吗 你这踢足球的下贱东西
Nor tripped neither, you base football player!
感谢你伙计 你帮了我 我非常喜欢你
I thank thee, fellow. Thou servest me, and I'll love thee.
站起来 快滚
Come, sir, arise, away.
滚  滚
Away, away.
让我也把他雇下来吧 这是我的鸡冠帽
Let me hire him, too.
啊 我的乖乖
-Here's my coxcomb. -How now, my pretty knave?
-你好吗 -伙计 你最好接过我的鸡冠帽
-How dost thou? -Sirrah, you were best take my coxcomb.
-为什么  为什么
-Why, Fool? -Why?
这个伙计已经赶走了他的两个女儿
This fellow has banished two of his daughters
赐福于第三个女儿
and did the third a blessing against his will.
你如果要跟随他 必须带上我的鸡冠帽
If thou follow him, thou must needs wear my coxcomb.
啊 老伯
How now, nuncle?
真希望我有两顶鸡冠帽和两个女儿
Would I had two coxcombs and two daughters.
为什么   孩子
Why, boy?
如果我把我所有的家私都给了她们 至少我的鸡冠帽还是我的
If I gave them all my living I'd keep my coxcombs myself.
这顶是我的 再去你的女儿那里讨一顶吧
There's mine. Beg another of thy daughters.
不准叫我傻瓜 小子
Dost thou call me fool, boy? Eh?
你把其他所有的尊号都送了别人
All thy other titles thou hast given away.
只有这一个是与生俱来
That thou wast born with.
他说的不完全是蠢话 陛下
This is not altogether fool, my lord.
你什么时候开始这么喜欢唱歌的 小子?
When were you wont to be so full of songs, sirrah?
老伯 自从你把你的女儿当做母亲 我就常常唱起歌了
I have used it, nuncle, e'er since thou madest thy daughters thy mothers.
小子 我们要鞭打你
Sirrah, we'll have you whipped.
我不知道你跟你的女儿们究竟是什么亲戚
I marvel what kin thou and thy daughters are.
他们会因为我说的是真话而鞭打我
They'll have me whipped for speaking true,
你又因为我说谎而鞭打我
thou'lt have me whipped for lying.
有时我还会因为沉默而被鞭打
And sometimes I am whipped for holding my peace.
我宁愿做任何事也不愿做傻瓜
I had rather be any kind of thing than a fool.
但我宁可做个傻瓜 也不愿意做你 老伯
-And yet I would not be thee, nuncle
你把你的聪明从两边削去 削的中间什么都不剩
Thou hast pared thy wit on both sides and left nothing in the middle.
瞧 那削下的一块来了
Here comes one of the parings.
嗯
Hm.
怎么了 女儿 为什么你的脸上写满怒气
How now, daughter? What makes that frontlet on?
我看你近来老是皱着眉头
Methinks you are too much of late i' the frown.
不光是这个肆无忌惮的佣人
Not only, sir, this your all-licensed fool,
还有你那些蛮横的随从 时时叫嚣挑衅
but other of your insolent retinue do hourly carp and quarrel,
种种不法的暴行 实在叫人忍无可忍
breaking forth in rank and not-to-be-endured riots.
父亲 我本来以为 只要让你了解这些事情
Sir, I had thought by making this well known unto you
就能找到补救的办法
to have found a safe redress
可照你自己最近的所言所行来看
but now grow fearful, by what yourself too late have spoke and done,
你分明是在为他们撑腰 有意纵容这种恶行
that you protect this course and put it on by your allowance.
你还是我的女儿吗
-Are you our daughter? Hm?
我希望你明智一点
I would you would make use of your good wisdom
你最近总是心怀不满
whereof I know you are fraught
动不动就乱发脾气
and put away these dispositions
这样实在有失一个做长辈的体统
which of late transport you from what you rightly are.
马被车子拖着走的时候 就算一头蠢驴也能发现事情颠倒了
May not an ass know when the cart draws the horse?
呼 玖格 我爱你!
Whoop, Jug, I love thee!
这里有人认识我吗?
Does any here know me?
这不是李尔吗
This is not Lear.
是李尔在走路吗 在说话吗
Does Lear walk thus? Speak thus?
他的眼睛呢?
Where are his eyes?
他的知觉迷乱了吗 他的神智麻木了吗
Either his notion weakens, or his discernings are lethargied.
哈,还醒着吗?
Ha, waking?
没有的事
'Tis not so.
谁能告诉我我是谁?
Who is it that can tell me who I am?
李尔的影子
Lear's shadow.
你叫什么名字 小姐?
Your name, fair gentlewoman?
-哈
-Huh?
父亲 近来您就喜欢开这样的玩笑
This admiration, sir, is much o'th'savour of other your new pranks.
我恳求你明白我的苦衷
I do beseech you to understand my purposes aright.
您这样一个可敬的长者 应该明智一些
As you are old and reverend, should be wise.
您在这里养的一百个骑士和随从
Here do you keep a hundred knights and squires,
全都是些胡闹放荡 胆大妄为之辈
men so disordered, so debauched and bold
好好的宫廷被他们的任意妄为搅得像个闹哄哄的客栈
that this our court, infected with their manners, shows like a riotous inn.
噢
Oh...
所以请您依了我的要求
Be then desired by her that else will take the thing she begs
酌量减少您的随从人数吧
a little to disquantity your train.
地狱里的魔鬼 把我的侍从全招集起来
Darkness and devils! Call my train together.
没有良心的混账 我不会麻烦你了
Degenerate bastard, I'll not trouble thee.
我还有一个女儿呢
Yet have I left a daughter.
你打我的佣人 而你那班乌合之众胆敢对上位者呼来喝去
You strike my people and your rabble make servants of their betters.
唉 后悔的太晚了!
Woe that too late repents!
啊 你也来了
O, you, sir, you, are you come?
这是你的意思吗 告诉我
Is it your will? Speak, sir.
陛下请不要生气 科迪莉亚只是犯了一些微不足道的错误
- Pray, sir, be patient. - O most small fault,
怎么在我眼里变得如此丑恶
how ugly didst thou in Cordelia show,
像一座强力的机器 扭曲了我的天性
which, like an engine, wrenched my frame of nature from the fixed place,
抽干了我心里的慈爱
drew from my heart all love,
灌入了苦涩的怨恨
and added to the gall.
李尔 李尔 李尔!痛打这糊涂脑袋吧
O Lear, Lear, Lear! Beat at this gate that let thy folly in
这欢迎愚蠢 赶走智慧的糊涂脑袋
and thy dear judgement out.
我的人跟我走
Go, go, my people!
陛下 我是无辜的 我不知道你为什么如此生气
My lord, I am guiltless as I am ignorant of what hath moved you.
也许不是你的错 公爵
It may be so, my lord.
听着 造化的女神 听我的哭诉
Hear, Nature, hear, dear goddess, hear!
如果你想使这畜生生儿育女 请改变你的旨意吧
Suspend thy purpose if thou didst intend to make this creature fruitful.
剥夺她生育的能力!
Into her womb convey sterility!
使她的器官枯竭
Dry up in her the organs of increase,
让他卑贱的身躯永远生不出一个子女来使他享受荣耀
and from her derogate body never spring a babe to honour her.
如果她必须生产 请让她生下一个忤逆的孩子
If she must teem, create her child of spleen,
让那个孩子成为他终生的折磨
that it may live and be a thwart disnatured torment to her.
让她年轻的额角过早刻上皱纹
Let it stamp wrinkles in her brow of youth,
这样他就能体会到 有一个忘恩负义的孩子
that she may feel how sharper than a serpent's tooth it is
比毒蛇的牙齿更令人痛入骨髓
to have a thankless child.
走吧 我们走
Away, away!
我的老天爷 这到底是怎么回事
Now, gods that we adore, whereof comes this?
你不用知道原因
Never afflict yourself to know more of it,
由着他发脾气吧
but let his disposition
喂 你 你这小子
O you, you, sirrah!
还不到半个月 就把我的随从一下子裁撤了50名吗
What, fifty of my followers at a clap, within a fortnight?
-什么事 陛下? -我待会儿告诉你
- What's the matter, sir? - I'll tell thee!
我真感到惭愧 你就有力量撼动我的大丈夫气概
Life and death! I am ashamed that thou hast power to shake my manhood thus.
愿毒风和恶雾袭击你
Blasts and fogs upon thee!
愿一个父亲的诅咒刺透你的五官百窍 留下深不可测的疮痍
The untented woundings of a father's curse pierce every sense about thee!
就这样吧 我还有一个女儿
Let it be so. Yet have I left a daughter...
…我敢肯定 他是一个善良、孝顺的人
...who, I am sure, is kind and comfortable.
她听见你这样对待我
When she shall hear this of thee,
一定会用指甲抓破你豺狼一样的脸
with her nails she'll flay thy wolvish visage.
你会发现我将恢复原状
Thou shalt find that I'll resume the shape
你以为我一辈子都做不到了
which thou dost think I have cast off for ever.
但我会重振雄风 你等着瞧吧
Thou shalt, I warrant thee.
走吧 我们走
Away, away.
你听到了吗
Do you mark that?
虽然我十分爱你 可是我不能这样偏心 戈纳瑞
I cannot be so partial, Goneril, to the great love I bear you...
随你的便吧
Pray you, content.
奥斯瓦德
Oswald!
你这七分奸三分傻的人 跟上你的主人
You, sir, more knave than fool, after your master!
李尔老伯 李尔老伯 等等
Nuncle Lear, nuncle Lear, tarry.
-一百个骑士  -带上佣人一起走
- A hundred knights? -Take the fool with thee!
让他随身带着一百个骑士 可真是万全之计
'Tis politic and safe to let him keep at point a hundred knights!
只要他做了一个梦 听了一句谣言 转了一个念头 心生不快不满
Yes, that on every dream, each buzz, each fancy, each complaint, dislike,
这老糊涂便会耍性子 凭他们的力量 把我们的性命置于股掌间
he may enguard his dotage with their powers and hold our lives in mercy.
奥斯华德 喊你呢
Oswald, I say!
也许你多虑了
Well, you may fear too far.
总比大意稳当
Safer than trust too far.
我知道他想什么
I know his heart.
他所说的话我已写在给我妹妹的信上了
What he hath uttered I have writ my sister.
如果她不听我劝告
If she sustain him and his hundred knights
还要收留他和那一百个骑士
when I have showed th'unfitness...
奥斯华德 去找我妹妹 告诉她我特别害怕
Oswald, away to my sister. Inform her full of my particular fear,
此外 你自己再添几条理由 让其更令人信服
and thereto add such reasons of your own as may compact it more.
你快去快回
Get you gone, and hasten your return.
如果一个人的脑筋长在脚跟上 难道他就不会有冻疮的危险吗
If a man's brains were in's heels, were't not in danger of chilblains?
会啊 孩子
Ay, boy.
那你高兴点儿吧
Then, I prithee, be merry.
你的脑筋又不用穿了拖鞋走路 唉唉
Thy wit shall not go slipshod. Oy oy!
你能说出一个人的鼻子为什么长在脸中间吗?
Thou canst tell why one's nose stands in the middle of one's face?
不知道
No.
还能为什么呢 为了把两眼睛各放一边呀
Why, to keep one's eyes of either side's nose...
额
Ah...
鼻子闻不出的东西 可以用眼睛瞧个仔细
...that what a man cannot smell out, he may spy into.
唉唉
Oy oy!
我对不起她
I did her wrong.
你知道牡蛎怎样造它的壳吗
Canst tell how an oyster makes his shell?
不知道
No.
我也不知道
Nor I neither.
但是我知道为什么蜗牛有房子
But I can tell why a snail has a house.
-为什么?-为了把脑袋放进去
-Why? -Why, to put's head in.
为了不把它送给女儿 害自己无处安顿
Not to give it away to his daughters and leave his horns without a case.
我也顾不上什么天性了
I will forget my nature.
我这父亲待他们这么好
I'm so kind a father.
北斗七星为什么只有七星
The reason why the seven stars
其中有个绝妙的理由
are no more than seven is a pretty reason.
因为没有第八颗吗
-Because they are not eight. -Yes, indeed.
你会成为一个好佣人的
Thou wouldst make a good fool.
忘恩负义的禽兽
Monster ingratitude.
如果你是我的佣人 老伯
If thou wert my fool, nuncle,
我要把你打一顿 因为你还没到你的年纪 你就老了
I'd have thee beaten for being old before thy time.
怎么说
How's that?
你应该懂些世故再老呀
Thou shouldst not have been old till thou hadst been wise.
哦 我不要发疯
O, let me not be mad.
不是发疯 上天啊
Not mad, sweet heavens.
按耐住怒火
Keep me in temper.
我不要疯掉
I would not be mad.
车马已备好 陛下
- Ready, my lord.
来吧,男孩
Come, boy.
哥哥,听我说句话
Brother, a word.
下来 哥哥
Ascend, brother, I say.
你快逃离这里
O sir, fly this place.
有眼线告诉了他你的藏身之处
Intelligence is given where you are hid.
康沃尔公爵马上就要来了 他和里甘一起来了
The Duke of Cornwall's coming hither now, in haste and Regan with him.
-你真的没有说什么反对他的话吗 ?  -我真没有
-Have you nothing said upon his party? -I am sure of it...
-嘘  -我没说过
-Sh... -Not a word.
我听到父亲过来了
I hear my father coming.
救命   救命
Help! Help!
快逃 我的哥哥 逃吧
-Fly, brother! Fly!
来人啊
Help!
我曾经见过醉汉 闹着玩儿的割破皮肉 那可比这要厉害
I've seen drunkards do more than this in sport.
来人
Help!
各就各位
Take your positions!
-那个畜生在哪 -他站在这黑暗中
-Where is the villain? -Here stood he in the dark,
喃喃地念着邪恶的咒语 见神见鬼地请月亮帮他的忙
mumbling of wicked charms, conjuring the moon to stand auspicious mistress.
-他在哪里?-看 父亲 我流血了
-But where is he? -Look, sir, I bleed.
那个恶棍在哪儿 埃德蒙
Where is the villain, Edmund?
-往那边逃了 父亲 他见自己无法
Fled this way, sir, when by no means he could...
抓住他  快    快追
Pursue him! Ho! Go after!
“无法”怎样
"By no means" what?
无法说服我谋害您
Persuade me to the murder of your lordship.
他永远不会逍遥在外 抓到了就叫他活不成
Not in this land shall he remain uncaught, and found, dispatch.
是公爵 我要关闭所有的城门 公爵一定会答应我的要求
It is the duke. All ports I'll bar, the duke must grant me that.
那不孝子逃不掉的
The villain shall not 'scape.
我忠诚孝顺的孩子
And of my land, loyal and natural boy,
我会想法子让你继承我的土地
I'll work the means to make thee capable.
怎么了 伯爵
How dost, my lord?
啊 夫人 我这颗年老的心已经碎了 碎了
O madam, my old heart is cracked, 'tis cracked.
什么 我父亲的教子要取你性命
What, did my father's godson seek your life?
噢 夫人 夫人 这种事真叫人丢脸
O lady, lady, shame would have it hid.
他和我父亲那帮横行不法的骑士 不是常在一起吗
Was he not companion with the riotous knights that tended upon my father?
-我不知道 夫人 太糟糕了 太糟糕了 -是的 夫人 他常和那伙人混在一起
-I know not, madam. 'Tis too bad, too bad. -Yes, madam, he was of that consort.
哦 那就不足为奇了 受了那种坏影响
Oh, no marvel then though he were ill affected.
今晚我收到了我姐姐的信了
I have this present evening from my sister
他们的行径她全告诉我了
been well informed of them and with such cautions
还警告我 他们要是想住到我家里来 我最好别在家
that if they come to sojourn at my house, I'll not be there.
我也不会呆在家里的 相信我 里根
Nor I, assure thee, Regan.
爱德蒙  我听说你很孝敬你的父亲
Edmund, I hear you have shown your father a child-like office.
这是身为儿子的本分 殿下
It was my duty, sir.
您看他手臂上的伤 就是因为想要抓住那畜生而受的
He received this hurt you see, striving to apprehend him.
派人去追捕他了吗 - 已经去追了 殿下
-Is he pursued? -Ay, my good lord.
如果抓住他了 我们一定不会再让他造次
If he be taken, he shall never more be feared of doing harm.
至于你 爱德蒙
For you, Edmund,
你的那忠孝天性值得赞赏 我们正需要值得信赖的人 你是头一个被我们选中的
natures of such deep trust we shall much need. You we first seize on.
殿下 我愿意为您尽忠效命
I shall serve you, sir, truly, however else.
我代他感谢您的恩惠 谢谢您能看得起他
For him I thank your grace.
你还不知道我们为什么造访你
You know not why we came to visit you.
尊贵的葛罗斯特 我们趁着夜色前来
Thus out of season, threading dark-eyed night,
如此不合时宜 实在是因为有些事情
occasions, noble Gloucester, of some prize,
必须请教一下您的意见
wherein we must have use of your advice.
-它们嗅到他的气味了
- They've got the scent!
继续搜 把他找出来
Go on, find him!
往前走 一直搜
Forwards! Keep moving forwards!
-你是这屋的人吗 朋友  -是的
-Art of this house, friend? -Ay.
-车停在哪好  -停泥地里吧
-Where may we stop? -In the mire.
行行好 大家都是朋友 告诉我吧
I prithee, if thou lovest me, tell me.
-谁是你的朋友   -我才不想理你
-I love thee not. -Why, then I care not for thee.
要是我们打一架 看你理不理我
If I had thee in a ring I'd make thee care for me.
你为什么对我这样 我根本不认识你
Why dost thou use me thus? I know thee not.
-你这家伙 我可认识你 -你知道我什么
-Fellow, I know thee. -What dost thou know me for?
一个无赖 流氓
A knave, a rascal,
一个下贱的、狂妄的、浅薄的 像个
a base, proud, shallow, beggarly,
只有三套衣服 身家不过百镑的乞丐 穿着精仿袜的卑鄙无赖
three-suited, hundred-pound, filthy worsted-stocking knave.
你这可怕的家伙 为什么要骂我
Why, what a monstrous fellow art thou, thus to rail on one
我们压根都不认识
that neither knows thee nor is known of thee.
还说你不认识我 你脸皮真厚
What a brazen-faced varlet art thou to deny thou knowest me.
我曾把你踢倒在地 还在王上的面前打过你
I tripped up thy heels and beat thee before the king.
我要在月光底下把你剁得稀烂 你这个混蛋
I'll make a sop of the moonlight of you, you whoreson.
滚开 我和你半毛钱关系都没有
Away! I have nothing to do with thee.
你这混蛋
You rascal!
你让一个傀儡女儿反对她的父王 你这混蛋
You take the puppet's part against the royalty of her father, you rogue.
-救命啊 杀人啦 救命啊
-Help! Murder! Help! -
-站住 你这混蛋 站住 你这奴才
-Stand, you rogue! Stand, you slave!
救命啊
Help!
-救命!救命!-怎么了 出什么事了
-Help! Help! -How now, what's the matter?
好小子 你也想挨拳头吧
With you, goodman boy!
要是你来 我也会揍你 来吧 小主人
If you please come, I'll beat ye. Come on, young master!
-这发生什么事了 - 马上住手 否则小心你们的命
-What's the matter here? -Peace, upon your lives!
违令擅动者死
He dies that strikes again!
-发生什么事了
-What is the matter?
这一个从我姐姐和国王那儿来的信使
The messenger from our sister and the king.
你的身份有什么不同 说吧
What is your difference? Speak.
殿下 这个老恶棍 我已经饶了他的命
Sir, this ancient ruffian, whose life I have spared...
你这个混球 你多此一举的信
You whoreson zed, you unnecessary letter...
住口 小子 难道你不懂规矩吗
Peace, sirrah! Know you no reverence?
-我当然知道规矩 殿下 可我实在气不过 也就顾不得了 -你为什么这样生气
-Yes, sir, but anger hath a privilege. - Why art thou angry?
我生气世上竟还有像他这般毫无忠诚可言的奴仆
That such a slave as this should walk the world, who wears no honesty.
-他做错什么了 - 我就不喜欢他的嘴脸
- What is his fault? -His countenance likes me not.
也许你也不喜欢我的面孔、他的面孔
No more perchance does mine, nor his,
还有她的面孔
nor hers.
我曾经见过一些面孔
I have seen better faces in my time
比现在我面前的这一张张嘴脸好的太多了
than stands on any shoulder that I see before me at this instant.
你这固执的老贼
You stubborn, ancient knave.
让我们好好教教你该怎么说话做事
We'll teach you.
我可是王上的人
I serve the king!
凭着我的生命和荣誉起誓 他必须像这样跪在这里直到...明天中午为止
As I have life and honour, here shall he stay until... noon?
到中午
Till noon?
到明天夜里 殿下
Till tomorrow night, my lord.
为什么 夫人 就算我是您父亲的狗 您也不该这样对待我
Why, madam, if I was your father's dog, you should not use me so.
正是因为他的走狗 我才这样对你
Sir, being his knave, I will.
这正是我们的姐姐说起过的那个家伙
This is a fellow of the selfsame colour our sister speaks of.
王上一定会心生不快
The king his master needs must take it ill
要是知道您如此轻蔑他的人
that he, so slightly valued in his messenger,
-把他像这样捆起来
-should have him thus restrained.
我会负责的
I'll answer that.
我的姐姐要是知道她的使者被人这样侮辱殴打 肯定心里更加不快
My sister may receive it much more worse to have her gentleman abused, assaulted.
-走吧 -撤下
- Come, away. -Dismissed!
很抱歉 朋友 我会替你求情的
I'm sorry for thee, friend. I'll entreat for thee.
请别这么做 大人
Pray do not, sir.
（您遭到这般对待）是公爵的不是 王上一定会见怪的
The duke's to blame in this. 'Twill be ill taken.
我听见了内心深处的呼唤
I heard myself proclaimed.
爱德伽
Edgar!
Edgar...
我...什么都
I... nothing...
不是
am.
他头戴着吊带袜
He wears cruel garters.
祝福您 尊贵的主人
Hail to thee, noble master.
是谁认错人了 把你锁在这
What's he that hath so much thy place mistook to set thee here?
是他俩 您的女婿和女儿
It is both he and she, your son and daughter.
-不可能 -就是他们
-No. -Yes.
-我说了不可能是他们 -就是他们
-No, I say. -I say, yea.
-凭着朱庇特起誓 不可能有这样的事 -凭着朱诺起誓 确有其事
-By Jupiter, I swear no. -By Juno, I swear ay.
我那女儿呢 快给我的仆从松绑
Where is this daughter? Give me my servant forth!
拒绝和我说话
Deny to speak with me?
他们是病了 累了 还是整夜奔波
They are sick? They are weary? They have travelled all the night?
哈 仅仅是想知道
Ha! Mere fetches.
这是要反叛逃离的意思
The images of revolt and flying off.
给我一个更好的回答
Fetch me a better answer.
去告诉公爵和他的妻子 我现在就要和他们讲话
Go tell the duke and his wife I'd speak with them, now, presently.
叫他们出来听我说话
Bid them come forth and hear me,
否则我在房间门口一直敲鼓 吵得他们睡不着 直到他们求饶为止
or at their chamber door I'll beat the drum till it cry sleep to death.
我但愿你们之间相安无事
I would have all well betwixt you.
哦 我的心 我狂躁的心..冷静一下
O me, my heart, my rising heart... But down...
你向它吆喝吧 老伯伯
Cry to it, nuncle,
就像厨娘把活鳗鱼放进面糊里时候的那样
as the cockney did to the eels when she put 'em in the paste alive.
她拿起手里的棍子在它们的头上敲打 大喊道
She knapped 'em on their coxcombs with a stick and cried,
“下去 坏东西 下去 ”
"Down, wantons, down!"
哦 二位早安
Oh, good morrow to you both.
祝福您 陛下
Hail to your grace.
-很高兴看见您-里根 我想你一定高兴看见我的
-I am glad to see your highness. -Regan. I think you are.
我完全有理由这么想
I have good reason to think so.
你被放出来啦
Oh, are you free?
你姐姐对我太不敬了
Thy sister's naught.
里根 她的无情的凶恶像饿鹰的利喙一样猛啄我的心
O Regan, she hath tied sharp-toothed unkindness like a vulture here.
我几乎没法儿告诉你
I can scarce speak to thee.
你不会相信她堕落了到什么地步
Thou'lt not believe with how depraved a quality...
-哦 里根 - 我恳求您 忍着点儿吧
-O Regan! -I pray you, sir, take patience.
我想她不会对您有失敬
I have hope you less know how to value her desert
而恐怕是您不能谅解她的苦心
than she to scant her duty.
这是什么意思
Say, how is that?
我想姐姐决不会有什么地方不尽孝道
I cannot think my sister in the least should fail her obligation.
要是她管束了您那班随从的放荡的行为
If, sir, perchance she hath restrained the riots of your followers,
自然有充分的理由 绝对不能怪她的
'tis on such ground and to such wholesome end as clears her from all blame.
我诅咒她
My curses on her.
父亲 你也老了
O sir, you are old.
已经快到生命的尽头了
Nature in you stands on the very verge of her confine.
应该让一个比您自己
You should be ruled and led
更明白您的境况的人管教管教您
by some discretion that discerns your state better than you yourself.
我劝您还是回到姐姐那
Therefore I pray you that to our sister you do make return.
对她赔一个不是
Say you have wronged her.
请求她的原谅
Ask her forgiveness?
你看这样像不像个样子
Do you but mark how this becomes the house?
“好女儿 我承认我老了 不中用啦”
"Dear daughter, I confess that I am old. Age is unnecessary."
“我跪在地上请求你能赏给我几件衣服穿 一张床睡 一些东西吃吧”
"On my knees I beg that you'll vouchsafe me raiment, bed, and food."
父亲 别在这丢人现眼了
Sir, these are unsightly tricks.
回我姐姐那儿去吧
Return you to my sister.
我再也不会回去了 里根
Never, Regan!
她撤了我一半的侍从 拿冷脸对我
She hath abated me of half my train, looked black upon me,
用她的毒蛇一般的嘴刺伤我的心
struck me with her tongue most serpent-like upon the very heart.
但愿上天蓄积的愤怒
All the stored vengeances of heaven
-一起降在她无情无义的头上 -呸呸呸 别说了
-fall on her ingrateful top! -Fie, sir, fie.
恶风吹打她的腹中的胎儿 让它生下地来就是个瘸子
Strike her young bones, you taking airs, with lameness!
啊
Ah...
迅疾的闪电啊 用你眩目的火焰射进她傲慢的眼睛里去吧
You nimble lightnings, dart your blinding flames into her scornful eyes!
烈日的熏灼下蒸发的瘴气啊 毁坏她的容颜
Infect her beauty, you fen-sucked fogs drawn by the powerful sun,
让她容颜不在
to fall and blister!
天上的神明啊 您要是对我发起怒来 也会这样咒我的
O the blest gods, so will you wish on me when the rash mood is on.
不 里根 你永远不会受我的诅咒
No, Regan, thou shalt never have my curse.
你天性温柔 绝不可能干出这等冷酷残忍的事
Thy tender-hefted nature shall not give thee o'er to harshness.
你姐姐眼里有股凶光 可是你的眼睛却是温柔而和蔼的
Her eyes are fierce, but thine do comfort and not burn.
你最懂得孝道
Thou better knowest the offices of nature,
儿女的责任 礼貌和滴水之恩的感激
bond of childhood, effects of courtesy, dues of gratitude.
你总还没有忘记我曾赐给你一半的国土
Thy half of the kingdom hast thou not forgot, wherein I thee endowed.
父亲 这就说远了
Good sir, to the purpose.
是谁绑了我的人
Who put my man i' the stocks?
-你的女主人来了吗 - 我
-Is your lady come? -I...
这是一个靠着主人暂时的得宠、狐假虎威
This is the slave whose easy, borrowed pride
倚势凌人的奴才
dwells in the fickle grace of her he follows.
-滚开 贱奴 不要让我看见你! -这是什么意思 陛下
-Out, varlet, from my sight! -What means your grace?
谁绑了我的仆人
Who stocked my servant?
里根 我希望你并不知道这件事
Regan, I have good hope thou didst not know on it.
谁来了
Who comes here?
神明啊
O heavens!
要是你爱老人 你认为子女应该孝顺他们的父母
If you do love old men, if your sweet sway allow obedience,
要是你自己也是老人 就不要无动于衷
if you yourselves are old, make it your cause.
降下你的愤怒来 帮我报仇吧
Send down and take my part.
看见我这一把胡须 不觉得惭愧吗
Art not ashamed to look upon this beard?
啊里根 你竟然愿意跟她握手吗
O Regan, will you take her by the hand?
为什么不能跟我握手呢 我干了什么错事
Why not by the hand, sir? How have I offended?
这并不违背您那轻率的言辞和陈旧的法案
All's not offence that indiscretion finds and dotage terms so.
啊 我的胸膛 你还撑得住吗
O sides, you are too tough. Will you yet hold?
我的人怎么给你们绑了起来
How came my man i' the stocks?
陛下 是我绑了他
I set him there, sir!
你 是你干的吗
You? Did you?
父亲 行行好吧 您太软弱了
I pray you, Father, being weak, seem so.
如果您现在仍旧回到姐姐那儿
If till the expiration of your month
撤掉您一半的侍从 等住满了一个月
you will return and sojourn with my sister, dismissing half your train,
就住到我这儿来
come then to me.
我现在不在自己家
I am now from home
也没有足够的东西提供给您 满足不了您的各种消遣
and out of that provision which shall be needful for your entertainment.
回到她那儿去 裁撤五十名侍从 不
Return to her and fifty men dismissed? No!
劝我寄他们篱下 还不如劝我当奴仆
Persuade me rather to be slave and sumpter to that detested groom.
悉听尊便 父亲
At your choice, sir.
我告诉你 女儿 不要把我逼急了
I prithee, daughter, do not make me mad.
我也不愿再打扰你了 我的孩子 再会吧
I will not trouble thee, my child. Farewell.
我们就此别过 从此不再相见
We'll no more meet, no more see one another.
噢
Oh!
可是你是我的肉、我的血、我的女儿
But yet thou art my flesh, my blood, my daughter.
还不如说是我身体上的一个恶瘤 我不得不承认你是我的
Or rather a disease that's in my flesh, which I must needs call mine.
你是我的腐败的血液里的一个疖子、一个瘀块
Thou art a boil, a plague sore,
一个肿毒的疔疮
an embossed carbuncle in my corrupted blood.
可是我不愿责骂你
But I'll not chide thee.
报应到时候总会来的 我不会祈求它快些降到你身上
Let shame come when it will, I do not call it.
我不会要求天雷把你劈死你 我也会向天神控诉你的忤逆
I do not bid the thunder-bearer shoot, nor tell tales of thee to high-judging Jove.
你回去仔细想一想
Mend when thou canst.
趁早痛改前非
Be better at thy leisure.
我有耐心等你
I can be patient.
我可以带着我的一百个骑士 跟里根住在一起
I can stay with Regan, I and my hundred knights.
这不太可能
Not altogether so.
现在没轮到我 我也没有准备好合适招待您的礼数
I looked not for you yet, nor am provided for your fit welcome.
父亲 听我姐姐的话吧
Give ear, sir, to my sister.
看着您这种愤怒的样子
For those that mingle reason with your passion
他们一定觉得您老了
must be content to think you old and so...
但姐姐清楚自己在做些什么
But she knows what she does.
-你确定你这样说话合适吗  -父亲 这是我真实的想法
-Is this well spoken? -I dare avouch it, sir.
怎么 五十个侍从 这不是很好吗
What, fifty followers? Is it not well?
再多一些有什么用处 是的
What should you need of more, yea, or so many,
如此多的侍从花费和拉帮结派都是一件危险的事
sith that both charge and danger speak 'gainst so great a number?
一间屋子里养了许多人 受着两个主人支配 怎么不会发生争闹
How in one house may many people under two commands hold amity?
这太难了 简直不可能
'Tis hard, almost impossible.
父亲 为什么不呢
Why might not you, my lord,
里根那找仆人或者我的人那里找人侍候您
receive attendance from those that she calls servants or from mine?
为什么不呢 请您只带二十五个人来
Why not, my lord? I do entreat you to bring but five-and-twenty.
超过这个数目 我是恕不招待的
To no more will I give place or notice.
我把一切都给了你们
I gave you all...
您给的正是时候
And in good time you gave it.
叫你们做我的代理人、保管者
Made you my guardians, my depositories.
什么 我只能带二十五个人 到你这儿来吗 里根 你是这样说的
What? Must I come to you with five-and-twenty? Regan, said you so?
父亲 我可以再说一遍 我只允许您带这么几个人来
And speak it again, my lord. No more with me.
嗯
Ah...
哈
Ha!
我愿意跟你去
I'll go with thee.
你的五十个人还比她的二十五个人多上一倍
Thy fifty yet doth double five-and-twenty,
你的孝心也比她大一倍
and thou art twice her love.
听我说 父亲
Hear me, my lord.
您需要的二十五个人 十个或者五个
What need you five-and-twenty, ten, or five to follow
我们家有两倍的人让您差遣和侍候您
in a house where twice so many have a command to tend you?
-仅仅需要一个 -我看一个也不需要
-What need one? -Reason not the need.
最卑贱的乞丐 也有他的不值钱的身外之物
Our basest beggars are in the poorest thing superfluous.
人生除了生理需求之外要是没有其他的享受 那和畜类的生活有什么分别
Allow not nature more than nature needs, man's life is cheap as beast's.
你是一位夫人
Thou art a lady.
如果你穿华丽的衣服只为了保暖
If only to go warm were gorgeous,
为什么 这根本不必穿盛装
why, nature needs not what thou gorgeous wear'st,
那不能保暖
which scarcely keeps thee warm.
-但对于真实的需要
-But for true need...
老天 让我耐心点
You heavens, give me that patience,
我需要耐心
patience I need!
神啊 你们看见我在这儿 一个可怜的老头子 被忧伤和老迈
You see me here, you gods, a poor old man, as full of grief as age,
折磨得好苦
wretched in both.
假如是你们鼓动这两个女儿的心 使她们忤逆她们的父亲
If it could be you that stir these daughters' hearts against their father,
那么请你们不要尽是愚弄我 叫我默然忍受吧
fool me not so much to bear it tamely.
让我的心里激起了刚强的怒火
Touch me with noble anger
别让妇人所恃为武器的眼泪
and let not women's weapons, water- drops,
玷污我作为男人的尊严
stain my man's cheeks.
不 你们这两个妖女
No, you unnatural hags!
我要向你们复仇 我要做出一些让全世界都
I will have such revenges on you both that all the world shall...
我将做这样的事
I will do such things.
我还不知道是什么事 但这些事情将会是
What they are yet I know not, but they shall be...
将是这世上最恐怖的
the terrors of the earth!
你们以为我会哭泣
You think I'll weep.
不我不会哭
No... I'll not weep!
虽然我有充分的理由哭泣
I have full cause of weeping
可是我宁愿让这颗心碎成万片
but this heart shall break into a hundred thousand flaws
也不愿流下一滴泪来
or ere I'll weep.
啊 傻瓜
O Fool...
我要疯了
I shall go mad.
暴风雨要来了
'Twill be a storm.
这屋子是容不下父亲和他的那帮人的
The old man and his people cannot be well bestowed here.
是他自己不好 放着安逸的日子不过
'Tis his own blame hath put himself from rest,
一定要吃些苦头 才知道自己的愚蠢
and must needs taste his folly.
单是他一个人 我倒也很愿意收留他 其他人不行
For his particular I'll receive him gladly, but not one follower.
我也是这个意思 葛罗斯特伯爵呢
So am I purposed. Where is my Lord of Gloucester?
跟老头子出去了
Followed the old man forth.
王上正在盛怒之中
The king is in high rage.
-他要到哪去 -我不知道
-Whither is he going? -I know not.
还是不要管他 随他自己的意思吧
'Tis best to give him way. He leads himself.
伯爵 您千万不要留他
My lord, entreat him by no means to stay.
唉 这妖风刮得真大
Alack, the high winds do sorely ruffle.
田野里正刮着狂风
几英里内连灌木丛都没有
For many miles about there's scarce a bush.
伯爵 对于刚愎自用的人 只好让他们自己招致的灾祸
O sir, to wilful men the injuries that they themselves procure
-来教训他们 -关上门 伯爵
must be their schoolmasters. Shut up your doors.
关上门 伯爵
Shut up your doors, my lord.
风啊吹吧 撕裂你的脸颊 狂风 吹呀
Blow, winds, and crack your cheeks!
瀑布一样的倾盆大雨
Rage, blow, you cataracts and hurricanoes,
倾泻下来吧 淹没尖塔和屋顶
spout till you have drenched our steeples, drown'd the cocks!
如思想一般 迅捷的硫磺电火
You sulphurous and thought-executing fires,
劈碎橡树的巨雷先驱
vaunt-couriers of oak-cleaving thunderbolts, singe my white head!
震撼一切的雷电啊
And thou, all-shaking thunder,
把这生长繁密的土地击平吧
strike flat the thick rotundity o'th'world,
打碎造物的模型
crack nature's moulds,
不要留下任何一颗种子 以免生出忘恩负义的人
all germens spill at once that make ingrateful man.
老伯 回去吧
Good nuncle, in!
向你的女儿们祈求原谅吧
Ask thy daughters' blessing.
尽管轰鸣吧 喷发火焰 倾泼雨水
Rumble thy bellyful! Spit, fire! Spout, rain!
我不责怪你们的无情
I tax not you, you elements, with unkindness.
随你们高兴 降下可怕的威力来吧
Then let fall your horrible pleasure.
我就站在这 任你们驱使
Here I stand, your slave,
一个可怜 衰弱无力 受人鄙视的老头子
a poor, infirm, weak and despised old man.
脑袋只要够灵光 就有屋顶来遮挡
- -He that has a house to put his head in has a good headpiece.
陛下 您在这吗
-Alas, sir, are you here? -
伟大的神灵在我们头顶掀起这场可怕的骚动
Let the great gods that keep this dreadful pudder o'er our heads
让他们去找寻他们的敌人吧
find out their enemies now.
我是个并没有犯下什么罪 却受了很大冤屈的人
I am a man more sinned against than sinning.
陛下 这附近有一间茅屋
Gracious my lord, hard by here is a hovel.
有好的主人会借它替你挡挡风雨
Some friendship will it lend you 'gainst the tempest.
我的脑子开始乱了
My wits begin to turn.
过来 我的孩子 你怎么了 我的孩子
Come on, my boy. How dost, my boy?
你冷吗 我也冷
Art cold? I am cold myself.
来 带我到你的茅屋去 可怜的傻小子
Come, your hovel. Poor fool and knave,
我的心中也为你感到悲伤
I have one part in my heart that's sorry yet for thee.
有高清电影网出品 yougaoqing.com
新浪微博@摆渡字幕组译制
我不赞成这种不近人情的行为
I like not this unnatural dealing.
他们剥夺了我对自己房屋的使用权
They have taken from me the use of mine own house,
不许我提起他的名字 不许我替他说一句情
charged me on pain of perpetual displeasure
也不许我给他任何的救济 否则就要永远失去他们的欢心
neither to speak of him, entreat for him or any way sustain him.
-太野蛮 太不近人情了
Most savage and unnatural!
算了
Go to.
你别多说什么
Say you nothing.
我今晚收到一封信 说出来很危险
I have received a letter this night. 'Tis dangerous to be spoken.
陛下受到这样的凌虐 总有人会来替他报仇
These injuries the king now bears will be revenged.
有一只从法国来的军队已经在路上了
There is part of a power from France already footed.
我们必须站在国王的一边 我去找他
We must incline to the king. I will look for him.
你去陪公爵谈话 这样我的暗中救济便不会被察觉
Go you and maintain talk with the duke, that my charity be not of him perceived.
如果他问起我 就说我感觉不太舒服  已经睡了
If he ask for me, I'm ill and gone to bed.
哪怕我会因此而死 虽然他们的确这样恐吓过我
If I die for it, as no less is threatened me,
但国王是我的旧主 我不能坐视不理
the king, my old master, must be relieved.
你小心点
Pray you, be careful.
就是这里 陛下
Here is the place, my lord.
陛下 进去吧
Good my lord, enter.
在毫无遮蔽的夜里 这样的暴风雨谁也无法承受
The tyranny of the open night's too rough for nature to endure.
-让我一个人呆着 -陛下 进去吧
-Let me alone. -Good my lord, enter here.
你自己进去 找一个遮身的地方吧
Prithee, go in thyself, seek thine own ease.
这暴风雨令我无法仔细思考事情
This tempest will not give me leave to ponder on things would hurt me more.
但我待会儿会进去的 进去 孩子 你先走
But I'll go in. In, boy, go first.
我要祈祷 然后我就去睡觉
I'll pray. Then I'll sleep.
衣不蔽体的可怜人
Poor naked wretches, wheresoe'er you are,
都得忍受无情暴风雨的袭击
that bide the pelting of this pitiless storm,
你们无瓦遮头 食不果腹
how shall your houseless heads, your unfed sides,
衣不蔽体 如何抵挡这样的气候呢
your looped and windowed raggedness defend you from seasons such as these?
我从来没想过这种事
O, I have ta'en too little care of this.
安享荣华的人啊 睁开眼吧
Take physic, pomp!
到外面体验一下穷人所受的苦
Expose thyself to feel what wretches feel.
救命 救命 救命
Help, help, help me!
有鬼 有鬼
A spirit! A spirit!
什么
What?
你是什么人 在这茅屋里大呼小叫
-What art thou that dost grumble there? -Oh...
出来
-Come forth!
走开
Away!
恶魔就跟在我的背后
The foul fiend follows me!
到你的床上去暖暖身体吧
Go to thy bed and warm thee.
你是也因为把一切都给了两个女儿才落到这般田地吗
Didst thou give all to thy daughters and art thou come to this?
他没有女儿陛下
-He hath no daughters, sir. -Poor Tom!
该死的奸贼
Death, traitor!
除了残忍的女儿 世上也没什么东西能把人的天性驯服到如此卑贱的地步了
Nothing could have subdued nature to such a lowness but his unkind daughters.
上天保佑您过人的才智
Bless thy five wits!
汤姆好冷
Tom's... a-cold.
你本来是做什么的
What hast thou been?
一个心性高傲的仆人
A servingman, proud in heart and mind,
头发卷卷的 帽子上配着情人的手套
who curled my hair, wore gloves in my cap,
会讨女人的欢心
served the lust of my mistress's heart
干些见不得人的勾当
-and did the act of darkness with her...
当着上天的面
...in the sweet face of heaven.
道芬 我的孩子
Dolphin, my boy, boy, sessa!
人不过如此吗
Is man no more than this?
我们这三个人都已经失掉了本来的面目
Here's three on 's are sophisticated.
只有你才保全着天赋的原形
Thou art the thing itself.
人类在原始时代 不过是像你这样的一个赤裸 寒碜的
Unaccommodated man is no more but such a poor, bare, forked animal
两脚动物
as thou art. Ha!
脱掉 脱掉这些身外之物
Off, off, you lendings. Come, unbutton here.
老伯 别闹了
Prithee, nuncle, be contented.
这样危险的夜里是不能游泳的
'Tis a naughty night to swim in.
瞧 一团火走来了
Look, here comes a walking fire!
陛下 你怎么了
How fares your grace?
可怜的汤姆 吃的是泅水的青蛙
Poor Tom, that eats the swimming frog...
陛下没有别的人做伴了吗
Hath your grace no better company?
地狱里的魔王是一位绅士 汤姆好冷
The Prince of Darkness is a gentleman! Tom's a-cold...
跟我回去吧
Come with me.
我冒着危险出来找您
I have ventured to come seek you out
来把您带到有火炉有食物的地方去
and bring you where both fire and food is ready.
让我先跟这位哲学家说几句话
First let me talk a word with this philosopher.
陛下
Good my lord...
天上打雷是什么缘故
What is the cause of thunder?
陛下 接受他的好意 跟他回去吧
Good my lord, take his offer, go to the house!
-陛下 请您 -请您原谅 先生
- I do beseech your grace... -Cry you mercy, sir.
-大哲学家 让我们来做伴 -汤姆冷着呢
-Come, noble philosopher, your company. -Tom's a-cold.
进去 朋友 到里面去暖一暖
In, fellow, there. Keep thee warm.
不 这边走 陛下
No, no, no. This way, my lord.
我要带上他一起走 我要和我的大哲学家作伴   来吧 雅典人
With him. I will keep company with my philosopher. Come, good Athenian.
请您顺从他的意思 让他把那家伙也带进去
O, soothe him, good my lord. Let him take the fellow on.
您带着他来吧
Take him you on.
来吧先生  雅典人
Come, good sir, good Athenian.
呸 嘿 哼 我闻到了一股不列颠人的血腥
Fee, fie, fo and fum, I smell the blood of a British man.
这就是他谈起的那封信
This is the letter which he spoke of,
足以证实他私通法国的罪状
which approves him an intelligent party to the advantages of France.
同我去见我的公爵夫人
Come with me to my wife.
这信上所说的 如若属实
If the matter of this paper be certain, you have mighty business at hand.
不管真假 他已经使你成为葛罗斯特伯爵了
True or false, it hath made thee Earl of Gloucester.
找到你父亲
Seek out where thy father is,
that he may be ready for our apprehension.
这里比露天好一些 将就住吧
Here is better than the open air, take it thankfully.
我会尽我所能 再找点吃的用的
I will piece out the comfort with what addition I can.
我去去就来
I will not be long from you.
神明报答您的好心
The gods reward you for your kindness.
老伯 请告诉我 一个疯子
Prithee, nuncle, tell me whether a madman
是绅士呢还是平民
be a gentleman or a yeoman.
是国王
A king, a king!
是疯子才相信豺狼的驯良 马儿的健康
He's mad that trusts in the tameness of a wolf, a horse's health,
孩子的爱情 或是娼妓的盟誓
a boy's love, or a whore's oath.
这一切该结束了 我必须马上办了她们
It shall be done. I will arraign them straight!
来 请坐在这里 最博学的法官
Come, sit thou here, most learned justicer.
来做下吧 贤明的官长 坐下
Sit thou there, sapient sir. Sit!
现在 你们这两头母狐狸
And now, you she foxes...
陛下您怎么了
How do you, sir?
不要这样呆呆站着
Stand you not so amazed.
你愿意躺在褥垫上休息吗
Will you lie down and rest upon the cushions?
我要先看她们受审
I'll see their trial first.
把她们的证人带上来
Bring their evidence.
你 穿长袍的法官请入座
Thou robed man of justice, take thy place.
你 他执法的同僚 坐在他的旁边
And thou, his yoke-fellow of equity, bench by his side.
你是陪审官 也请坐
You are of the commission, sit you, too.
让他们秉公执法
Let us deal justly.
Mm.
先控诉她
Arraign her first.
这是戈瑞纳
'Tis Goneril.
我当着尊严的堂上起誓
I here take my oath before this honourable assembly
她曾经赶走她可怜的父王
she kicked the poor king, her father.
过来 夫人 您的名字是戈纳瑞吗
Come hither, mistress. Is your name Goneril?
唯有这点她不能否认
She cannot deny it.
对不起 我还以为您是一张折凳
Cry you mercy, I took you for a joint stool.
这边还有一位 瞧她满脸的横肉 就可以知道她的心肠是怎么样的
And here's another, whose warped looks proclaim what store her heart is made on.
拦住她
Stop her there.
举起你们的兵器 拔出你们的剑 点起火把 营私舞弊的法庭
Arms, arms, sword, fire, corruption in the place!
枉法的贪官 为什么放她逃走
False justicer, why hast thou let her 'scape?
哎 可怜啊 先生
O pity! Sir, whoa...
到哪里去了
Where...
你那常常夸口自己能保持住的耐心呢
Where's the patience now that you so oft have boasted to retain?
那些小狗
The little dogs and all...
特雷 布兰切 斯威特哈特 他们都朝我狂叫
Tray, Blanch, and Sweetheart, they bark at me.
让汤姆掉过脸来把他们吓走
Tom will throw his head at them.
滚开 你们这些恶狗
Avaunt, you curs!
叫他们剖开里甘的尸体
Then let them anatomise Regan,
看看她心里有些什么东西
see what breeds about her heart.
上天可有什么缘故 要造出这样硬的心肠
Is there any cause in nature that makes these hard hearts?
你 先生 我邀请你做为我一百名侍卫之一
You, sir, I entertain for one of my hundred,
只是我不喜欢你服装的样式
only I do not like your garments.
你也许想对我说 这是波斯风格 但还是换掉吧
You will say they are Persian, but let them be changed.
现在
Now...
好了 陛下
Good my lord...
请您躺下休息片刻
-Lie here and rest awhile. -
不要吵 不要吵
Make no noise, make no noise.
放下帐子
Draw the curtains.
那么
So, so...
我们到了早上就吃晚饭
We'll go to supper in the morning.
那我一到中午就去睡觉
And I'll go to bed at noon.
朋友这边来 陛下在哪里
Come hither, friend. Where is the king, my master?
这里 大人 但请不要打扰他 他的神智已经错乱了
Here, sir, but trouble him not. His wits are gone.
我的好朋友 请你把他抱起来 车已经准备好
Good friend, I prithee take him in thy arms. There is a litter ready.
快把他放进去 驾车去多佛
Lay him in it and drive toward Dover, friend,
到了那边会有人接待和保护你们
where thou wilt meet welcome and protection.
把他抱起来 抱起你的主人来
Take up! Take up thy master.
要是你再耽误半个钟头
If thou shouldst dally half an hour,
他和你的性命 以及一切前来救护他的人的性命 都要保不住了
his life, with thine and all who offer to defend him, stand in assured loss.
快快快 把他抱起来 跟我走
Take up, take up, and follow me.
最大的不幸是独抱牢愁
Who alone suffers suffers most in the mind,
任何的欢愉兜不上心头
leaving free thoughts and happy shows behind.
现在我的痛苦何等轻松
How light and portable my pain seems now,
使我折腰的也使国王鞠了躬
when that which made me bend made the king bow.
他有不孝逆女一如我有残忍的父亲
He childed... as I fathered.
汤姆
Tom...
走吧
Away.
法国军队已经登陆 快去搜寻那叛徒葛罗斯特
The army of France is landed. Seek out the traitor Gloucester.
快去找到那个反贼
Go seek the traitor Gloucester!
把他像贼一样捆起来
Pinion him like a thief.
带到我们面前
Bring him before us.
捉到之后立刻绞死
Hang him instantly.
把他的眼珠挖出来
Pluck out his eyes.
把他交给我处置
Leave him to my displeasure.
埃德蒙
Edmund...
护送我们的姐姐回去
Keep you our sister company.
我们对你叛变的父亲的刑罚
The revenges we are bound to take upon your traitorous father
不该让你看到
are not fit for your beholding.
-再会 亲爱的姐姐 -再会 敬爱的公爵
-Farewell, dear sister. -Farewell, sweet lord...
再会 我亲爱的妹妹
and sister.
埃德蒙 再会
Edmund, farewell.
看看谁来了
Who's there?
-是那个叛徒吗   -是那只忘恩负义的老狐狸
-The traitor? -Ingrateful fox, 'tis he.
把他枯瘪的手臂牢牢绑起来
Bind fast his corky arms.
你们这是什么意思?
What means your graces?
我的好朋友们  你们是我的客人
Good my friends, consider. You are my guests.
不要用这种无礼的手段对我
Do me no foul play, friends.
捆住他 再重复一遍
Bind him, I say.
绑紧些  绑紧些
Hard. Hard!
-这可恶的反贼  -你是个没有良心的女人  我不是反贼
-O filthy traitor. -Unmerciful lady as you are, I'm none!
把他绑在这张椅子上  混蛋  我要让你知道
To the chair bind him. Villain, thou shalt find...
天神在上  这还成什么话  你扯到我的胡子了
Ye kind gods! 'Tis most ignobly done to pluck me by the beard.
胡子这么白没想到却是一个反贼
So white and such a traitor.
你从我的下巴上扯下这些胡子来
These hairs which thou dost ravish
它们会控诉你的
from my chin will quicken and accuse thee.
我才是这里的主人
I'm your host!
你不应该用你强盗一般的手这样报答我的好客
With robbers' hands my hospitable favours you should not ruffle thus.
-你究竟要怎样?    -得了吧 说吧 先生
-What will you do? -Come, sir.
你从法国得到了什么书信?
What letters had you late from France?
你最好说实话因为我们已经知道了
Be simple-answered for we know the truth.
你跟那些叛徒有什么关系
What confederacy with traitors...
你把发疯的疯国王交到谁的手里了?  说
To whose hands you have sent the lunatic king. Speak.
我只收到了一封信  里面都是些猜测
I have a letter guessingly set down,
寄信的人是中立的
which comes from one that's of a neutral heart,
并不是一个敌人
and not from one opposed.
-噢  太狡猾了你  -一派鬼话
-Oh, cunning. -And false.
你把国王送到什么地方了?
Where hast thou sent the king?
送到了多佛
To Dover.
为什么送到多佛?  我们不是警告过你
Wherefore to Dover? Wast thou not charged at peril...
为什么送到多佛?  让他回答这个问题
Wherefore to Dover? Let him answer that.
我现在身陷窘境只好拼命了
I am tied to the stake and must stand the course.
为什么送到多佛?
Wherefore to Dover?
因为我不愿意看见你凶恶的指甲挖出他可怜的老眼
Because I would not see thy cruel nails pluck out his poor old eyes,
也不愿意看到你的姐姐用野猪般的牙齿咬他的肉体
nor thy fierce sister in his anointed flesh stick boarish fangs!
但我相信总有一天这些报应会降临到这些儿女身上的
But I shall see the winged vengeance overtake such children.
你不会看到那样的一天的
See't shalt thou never.
来  按住这椅子
Fellows, hold the chair.
啊
Oh!
谁要是希望能够活到老的过来帮帮我吧
He who will think to live till he be old give me some help!
噢  好惨
O cruel!
天哪
O you gods!
一只眼会嘲笑另一只的
One side will mock another.
另一只也挖掉吧
The other too.
如果你能看到什么报应
If you see vengeance...
住手  殿下  我从小就效劳您
Hold your hand, my lord. I have served you ever since I was a child,
但是我现在叫您住手这件事才是最好的效劳
but better service have I never done you than now to bid you hold.
怎么  你这狗东西
How now, you dog!
要是你的腮上长了胡子  我也要把它扯下来
If you did wear a beard upon your chin I'll shake it on this quarrel.
你要造反吗?
What do you mean?
好  那么
Nay then...
那我们拼一下吧
A peasant stand up thus!
我的大人
My lord...
你还有一只眼睛看到他的报应
You have one eye left to see some mischief on him.
我们把另一只也挖出来 以免他看到什么报应
Lest it see more, prevent it.
出来了  可恶的眼睛
Out, vile jelly...
你在叫的是一个极其憎恨你的人
Thou callest on him that hates thee.
仁慈的神明啊 请你宽恕我的过错
Kind gods, forgive me that
用福泽庇佑他吧
and prosper him.
把他撵出去 让他用他的狗鼻子为自己探路到多佛去吧
Go thrust him out at gates and let him smell his way to Dover.
啊 里甘……
Ah, Regan...
我的血止不住了
I bleed apace.
这伤受得可真不是时候
Untimely comes this hurt.
让我扶着你的手臂吧
Give me your arm.
一个最困苦 最卑贱 最为被命运所羞辱的人
To be worst, the lowest and most dejected thing of fortune
反而可以时刻抱有希望 无所畏惧
stands still in hope, lives not in fear.
我没有什么时候比现在更不幸了 但我还可能变得更加不幸
I am worse than ever I was. And worse I may be yet.
你的安慰对我没有什么作用 他们也许会害你
Thy comforts can do me no good at all, thee they may hurt.
我怎么可以现在离开 您的眼睛都看不见了啊
How now?
谁在那边
Who's there?
那是个可怜的疯子
It is a poor madman.
伙计 你要到哪儿去
Fellow, where goest?
在昨晚的暴风雨中 我也看到过一个像他这样的家伙
In the last night's storm I such a fellow saw.
让我觉得人不过如蝼蚁罢了
Made me think a man a worm.
我儿子的脸在脑海中浮现 但那时候我正憎恨着他
My son came then into my mind and yet my mind was then scarce friends with him.
后来我才听说一些其他的事情
I have heard more since.
我们于上帝而言就好像调皮小孩儿眼里的苍蝇
As flies to wanton boys are we to the gods.
他就是那个不穿衣服的家伙吗
Is that the naked fellow?
你走吧 帮我那一些衣服替这个可怜人遮盖一下身体……
Get thee away. Bring some covering for this naked soul...
天呐 老爷 他可是个疯子啊
Alack, sir. He is mad.
疯子给瞎子带路 正符合这个扭曲黑暗的时代
'Tis the times' plague when madmen lead the blind.
最要紧的是 快走吧
Above the rest, begone.
我会把我最好的衣服拿来 不管它会引起怎样的后果
I'll bring the best apparel that I have, come of it what will.
过来小伙子
Come hither, fellow.
你认识到多佛的路吗
Dost thou know Dover?
是的先生
Ay, master.
那边有一座悬崖 它那峭拔的绝顶
There is a cliff whose high
俯瞰着幽深的海水
and bending head looks fearfully in the confined deep.
把我带到那悬崖的边上
Bring me but to the very brim of it.
到了那我就不需要领路了
From that place I shall no leading need.
站好了
Stand still!
把眼睛望到这么低的地方 真是惊心炫目
How fearful and dizzy 'tis to cast one's eyes so low!
哦 我不能再看了
I'll look no more,
否则要头晕到栽下去了
lest my brain turn and the deficient sight topple down headlong.
领我到你站着的地方
Set me where you stand.
把手给我
Give me your hand.
哇
Whoa!
现在您距离悬崖边只有一尺了
You are now within a foot of the extreme verge.
无论如何 我也不愿跳下去
For all beneath the moon, would I not look upright.
放开我的手
Let go my hand.
你再走远一点儿
Go thou farther off.
向我告别一声 让我听见你走远了
Bid me farewell and let me hear thee going.
再会吧 好先生
Now fare ye well, good sir.
再会
With all my heart.
威严的神明啊
O you mighty gods!
我现在脱离这一个世界
This world I do renounce.
要是艾德嘉尚在人间
If Edgar live...
尚在人间
O bless him!
现在 朋友
Now, fellow...
我们再会了
Fare thee well.
我去了 先生 再会
Gone, sir. Farewell!
喂 这位先生 朋友
Ho you, sir? Friend?
你能听见吗 先生
Hear you, sir? Speak.
你是什么人 先生
What are you, sir?
走开 让我死
Away and let me die.
可是你还在呼吸
But thou dost breathe. Thy life's a miracle.
在对我说两句话吧
Speak yet again.
可是我没有跌下来
But have I fallen or no?
他就是从这可怕的悬崖绝顶上面跌下来的
From the dread summit of this chalky bourn. Look up a height.
-看 -唉 我没有眼睛
-Do but look up. -Alack, I have no eyes.
难道一个命苦的人 连死的权利都要被剥夺吗
Is wretchedness deprived that benefit to end itself by death?
把你的胳膊给我
Give me your arm.
起来
Up.
好 怎样
So, how is it? Feel you your legs?
你站住了
You stand.
很稳
Too well... Too well.
不要胡思乱想 安心忍耐
Bear free and patient thoughts.
正是他
It is he.
刚才还有人看见他 疯狂的像被飓风激动的怒海
He was met even now as mad as the vex'd sea.
拍一百个士兵 到繁茂的田野里 各处搜寻
A century send forth, search every acre in the high-grown field
把我父亲领来见我
and bring my father to our eye.
人的智慧能不能恢复他丧失的心神
What can man's wisdom in the restoring his bereaved sense?
法子是有的
There is means.
休息是滋养疲乏精神的保姆
Our foster-nurse of nature is repose.
快去找他  快去
Seek, seek for him,
我只怕他在补课控制的疯狂之中 会消灭了他失去主宰的生命
lest his ungoverned rage dissolve the life that wants the means to lead it.
那家伙弯弓的姿势 活像一个稻草人
That fellow handles his bow like a crow-keeper.
给我射一支一码长的箭试试看
Draw me a clothier's yard.
瞧瞧一只小老鼠
Ha! Look, look, a mouse!
别闹 别闹 这一块烘乳酪可以抓住它
Peace, peace. This piece of toasted cheese will do't.
我认识那个声音
I know that voice.
啊 飞的好 鸟儿
O, well flown, bird. I'th'clout, i'th'clout. Hewgh!
啊
Ah.
口令
Shoo. Give the word.
-茉荞兰 -过去
-Sweet marjoram. -Pass.
戈纳瑞 长着一把白胡须
Goneril with a white beard?
他们像狗一样向我献媚
They flattered me like a dog
说我在没有出黑须以前 就已经有了白须
and told me I had the white hairs in my beard ere the black ones were there.
我说一声“是” 他们就应一声“是”
To say "ay" and "no" to every thing I said!
我说一声“不”  他们就应一声“不”
"Ay" and "no" too was no good divinity.
这声音我记得很清楚 他不是我们的君王吗
The trick of that voice I do well remember. Is't not the king?
对 彻头彻尾的君王
Ay, every inch a king.
我只要一瞪眼睛 我的臣子就要吓得发抖
When I do stare, see how the subject quakes.
我赦免那个人的死罪 你犯的是什么案子 奸淫吗
I pardon that man's life. What was thy cause? Adultery?
你不用死
Thou shalt not die.
因奸淫而受死  不
Die for adultery? No...
让通奸的人多子多孙吧
Let copulation thrive,
因为葛罗斯特私生的儿子也比我合法的女儿
for Gloucester's bastard son was kinder to his father
更孝顺他的父亲
than my daughters got 'tween the lawful sheets.
淫风越盛越好 我巴不得他们替我多制造几个兵士出来
To it, luxury, pell-mell, for I lack soldiers.
他们的上半身虽然是女人 下半身却是淫荡的妖怪
Down from the waist they are centaurs, though women all above.
腰带以上属于天神 腰带以下全属于魔鬼
But to the girdle do the gods inherit, beneath is all the fiends'.
那是地狱 那是黑暗 那是火坑
There's hell, there's darkness, there's the sulphurous pit,
吐着熊熊的烈焰 发出熏人的恶臭 把一切烧成了灰 啐 啐 呸 呸
burning, scalding, stench, consumption. Fie, fie! Pah! Pah!
好掌柜 给我称一两麝香
Give me an ounce of civet, good apothecary,
让我解解我想象中的臭气
to sweeten my imagination.
钱在这儿
There's money for thee.
让我吻一吻那只手
Let me kiss that hand.
让我先把它揩干净 它上面有一股热烘烘的人气
Now, let me wipe it first, it smells of mortality.
你认识我吗
Dost thou know me?
我很记得你这双眼睛
I remember thine eyes well enough.
这是一封挑战书 你拿去读吧 瞧瞧他是怎么写的
Read thou this challenge. Mark but the penning of it.
即使每一个字都是一个太阳 我也瞧不见
Were all thy letters suns, I could not see.
-读呀 -什么
-Read. -What...
用眼眶读吗
With the case of eyes?
阿哈 你原来是这个意思吗
O ho, are you there with me?
你的头上也没有眼睛 你的袋里也没有银钱吗
No eyes in your head, nor no money in your purse?
你的眼眶真深
Your eyes are in a heavy case,
可是你却看见这世界的丑恶
yet you may see how this world goes.
我只能捉摸到他的丑恶
I see it feelingly.
什么
What, art mad?
一个人就是没有眼睛 也可以看见这个世界的丑恶
A man may see how this world goes with no eyes.
你还是去装上一副玻璃眼镜
Get thee glass eyes
像一个卑鄙的阴谋家似的 假装能够看见你所看不见的事情吧
and like a scurvy politician seem to see the things thou dost not.
来 来 来
Now, now, now...
要是你愿意为我的命运痛哭
If thou wilt weep my cause,
就把我的眼睛拿了去吧
take my eyes.
我知道你是什么人 你的名字是葛罗斯特
I know thee well enough. Thy name is Gloucester.
你必须忍耐
Thou must be patient.
你知道我们来到这世上
We came crying hither.
第一次嗅到了空气
Thou knowest the first time that we smell the air...
就哇哇的哭起来
we wail and cry.
让我讲一番道理给你听 你听着
I will preach to thee, mark.
当我们生下来的时候 我们因为来到了
When we are born, we cry
这个全是傻瓜的广大舞台之上 所以禁不住放声大哭
that we are come to this great stage of fools.
这顶帽子的样式很不错
Hey! This is a good block.
啊 啊
Oy, oy...
用毡呢钉在一队马儿的蹄上 倒是一个妙计
It were a delicate stratagem to shoe a troop of horse with felt. Sh!
我要把它实行一下 悄悄地偷进我那两个女婿的营里
I'll put it in proof, and when I have stolen upon these son-in-laws,
然后我就杀呀 杀呀 杀呀
then kill, kill, kill,
他在这儿 抓住他
-kill, kill, kill... -Hey! There he is. Lay hand upon him!
杀呀 杀呀 杀呀
Kill, kill, kill!
我是一个国王 你们知道吗
I'm a king, masters, know you that?
您是尊贵的陛下 我们服从您的旨意
-You are a royal one and we obey you. - Then there's life in it.
要去快去
Come, and you get it, you shall get it by running.
你的主人呢
Where's your master?
夫人 他在里边 可与之前判若两人
Madam, aloft, but never man so changed.
我告诉他法国军队登陆的消息 他听了只是微笑
I told him the French were landed. He laughed at it.
我告诉他 葛罗斯特谋反的时候
And of Gloucester's treachery when I informed him he called me sot,
说我颠倒是非
and told me I'd turned the wrong way out.
埃德蒙 你且回到军队去
Back, Edmund, to the troops.
催促他赶紧调集人马 交给你统帅
Hasten your musters and conduct your powers.
这个可靠的仆人可以替我们传达消息
This trusty servant shall pass between us.
不久你就会听到你女主人的命令
Ere long you are like to hear a mistress's command.
把东西带在身边
Wear this.
不要多说什么
Spare speech.
低下你的头来
Decline your head.
这一个吻 要是能够替我说话
This kiss, if it durst speak,
它会叫你的灵魂飞上天空
would stretch thy spirits up into the air.
你要明白我的心
Conceive...
再会吧
and fare thee well.
我愿意为你赴汤蹈火
Yours... in the ranks of death.
我最亲爱的葛罗斯特
My most dear Gloucester.
唉
Oh...
都是男人 却有天壤之别
The difference... of man and man.
哪一个女人不愿意为你贡献她的一切
To thee a woman's services are due.
我却让一个傻瓜侵占了我的眠床
A fool usurps my bed.
夫人 殿下来了
Madam, here comes my lord.
你太瞧不起人了
I have been worth the whistle.
啊 戈纳瑞
O Goneril...
你的价值还比不上那狂风吹在你脸上的尘土
You are not worth the dust which the rude wind blows in your face.
得了得了  全是些傻话
No more. The text is foolish.
智慧和仁义在恶人眼中看来都是恶的
Wisdom and goodness to the vile seem vile, filths savour but themselves.
不中用的懦夫 你的鼓呢
Milk-livered man, where's thy drum?
法国的国旗已经展开在我们宁静的国境上了
France spreads his banners in our noiseless land,
你这迂腐的傻子却坐着一动不动  只会说“唉 他为什么要这样呢”
whilst thou, a moral fool, sits still and cries, "Alack, why does he so?"
瞧瞧你自己吧 魔鬼
See thyself, devil!
恶魔的丑恶嘴脸 还不及一个恶魔般的女人那样丑恶万分
Proper deformity shows not in the fiend so horrid as in woman.
你这没有头脑的
Vain... fool.
我对姐妹两人都已经立下了爱情的盟誓
To both these sisters have I sworn my love,
他们彼此互怀嫉妒 就像一朝被蛇咬便见不得蛇的踪影
each jealous of the other as the stung are of the adder.
我应该选择哪一个呢
Which of them shall I take?
两个都要
Both? One?
还是一个也不要
Or neither?
要是两个全都留在世上 我就一个也不能到手
Neither can be enjoyed if both remain alive.
现在请你告诉我
Tell me but truly,
老老实实的告诉我
but then speak the truth.
你不爱我的姐姐吗
Do you not love my sister?
我只是按照我的名分敬爱她
In honoured love.
可是你从来没有深入我姐夫的禁地吗
But have you never found my brother's way to the forfended place?
您有这种想法可有失体统
That thought abuses you.
凭着我的名誉起誓 夫人 没有这样的事
No, by mine honour, madam.
我绝不答应她
I never shall endure her.
我亲爱的爵爷
Dear my lord...
不要跟她亲热
Be not familiar with her.
您放心吧
Fear me not.
她跟她的公爵丈夫来了
She and the duke, her husband.
贤妹久违了
Our very loving sister, well be-met.
伯爵 我听说
Sir, this I heard. The king is come to his daughter,
高呼不平的人们到他女儿的地方去了
with others whom the rigour of our state forced to cry out.
法国举兵侵犯我们的领土 我们不能容忍
It touches us, as France invades our land.
您说的有理
Sir, you speak nobly.
-这段话讲他做什么呢 -我们只需同心合力打退敌人
-Why is this reasoned? -Combine together 'gainst the enemy,
这些内部的纠纷 不是现在所要讨论的问题
for these domestic and particular broils are not the question here.
那我们讨论讨论应该采取的战略吧
Let's then determine on our proceeding.
-姐姐 你也跟我们一块儿去吗 -不
-Sister, you'll go with us? -No.
你怎么可以不去 来 请吧
'Tis most convenient. Pray, go with us.
哼 我明白你的意思
Oh, I know the riddle.
好 我去
I will go.
好肯特啊
O thou good Kent.
我怎么才能报答你这份良苦用心呢
How can I live and work to match thy goodness?
就是粉身碎骨 也不能抵偿你的大德
My life will be too short and every measure fail me.
夫人 只要自己的苦心被人了解 那就是莫大的报酬了
To be acknowledged, madam, is o'erpaid.
我所讲的话 句句属实 没有一分增减
All my reports go with the modest truth, nor more, nor clipped, but so.
我亲爱的父亲
O my dear father...
但愿我的嘴唇上
Restoration hang thy medicine on my lips
有治愈疯狂的灵药 让这一吻抹去了
and let this kiss repair those violent harms
我那两个姐姐加在你身上的无情的伤害吧
that my two sisters have in thy reverence made.
他醒来了
He wakes.
对他说些什么吧
Speak to him.
夫人 应该您跟他说
Madam, do you. 'Tis fittest.
父王陛下
How does my royal lord?
您好吗
How fares your majesty?
你们不应该
You do me wrong...
把我从坟墓中间拖了出来
to take me out of the grave.
你是一个有福的灵魂 我却缚在
Thou art a soul in bliss, but I am bound upon a wheel of fire
一个烈火的车轮上 我自己的眼泪
that mine own tears do scald like molten lead.
父亲 你认识我吗
Sir, do you know me?
你是一个灵魂 我知道
You are a spirit, I know.
你什么时候死的
Where did you die?
还是疯疯癫癫的
Still far, far wide.
他还没有完全清醒过来
He's scarce awake.
暂时不要惊扰它
Let him alone awhile.
我到过些什么地方  现在我在什么地方
Where have I been? Where am I?
明亮的白昼吗
Fair daylight?
我上了大当了
I am mightily abused.
我如果看见别人落到这一个地步 也要为他心碎而死
I should even die with pity to see another thus.
我不知道应该怎么说啊
I know not what to say.
我不愿发誓 这一双是我的手
I will not swear these are my hands.
让我试试看
Let's see.
这针刺上去是疼的
I feel this pin prick.
但愿我能知道我现在的状况
Would I were assured of my condition.
看着我 父亲
O look upon me, sir,
把您的手按在我的头上为我祝福
and hold your hand in benediction o'er me.
啊......
Ah...
您不要跪
You must not kneel.
请不要取笑我
Pray do not mock me.
我真是个愚蠢的傻老头
I am a very foolish fond old man,
都活了八十多岁了
fourscore and upward, not an hour more, nor less.
说实话 我怕是脑子不大好
And, to deal plainly, I fear I am not in my perfect mind.
我想我应该认识您 也认识这个人
Methinks I should know you and know this man.
可我不敢确定
Yet I am doubtful.
因为我不知道这是哪儿
For I am mainly ignorant what place this is
凭着我的能力也不知道什么时候穿的这身衣服
and all the skill I have remembers not these garments,
我也不知道昨晚在哪儿住的
nor I know not where I did lodge last night.
不要嘲笑我
Do not laugh at me,
因为 我也是个人
for, as I am a man,
我想这位夫人是我的孩子......
I think this lady to be my child...
考狄利娅
Cordelia.
我是......
And so I am...
我是
I am.
怎么哭了
Be your tears wet?
不要哭了
I pray thee... weep not.
就算你把毒药给我 我也会喝下去
If you have poison for me, I will drink it.
我知道你不爱我
I know you do not love me,
你的两个姐姐都虐待我
for your sisters have, as I do remember, done me wrong.
你虐待我还有理由 而他们没有
You have some cause, they have not.
谁都没有理由
No cause, no cause.
我在法国么
Am I in France?
-在您自己的国境内 陛下 -不要骗我
- In your own kingdom, sir. - Do not abuse me.
请宽心一点 夫人
Be comforted, good madam.
您看他已经平静下来了
The great rage, you see, is killed in him.
不要再多加烦扰他
Desire him to go in.
请陛下到里面去休息休息吧
Will it please your highness walk?
啊......你必须原谅我
Ah... You must bear with me.
请你既往不咎 宽恕我的罪过
Pray you now, forget and forgive.
我老了......
I am old...
还糊涂
and foolish.
开火
Fire!
掩护
Take cover!
等我回来 就安全了
If ever I return to you again, I'll bring you comfort.
愿你平安 先生
Grace go with you, sir.
先仔细检查一遍这片区域
On le recherche sur toute cette zone.
之后如果你愿意的话
Après nous pourrons déployer si vous voulez
我们可以在宫殿旁再布些人手
une autre troupe du c?té du chateau...
快离开那儿
Away!
老先生
Old man!
给我你的手 快离开那儿
Give me thy hand, away!
李尔王败了 他和他的女儿都被捉走了
King Lear hath lost, he and his daughter taken.
给我你的手 快走
Give me thy hand. Come on!
不了 先生
No further, sir.
我就在这等死吧
A man may rot even here.
您应该耐心忍受上天的安排
Men must endure their going hence even as their coming hither.
一切都是残忍的
Ripeness is all.
哦......哦......
Oh... Oh...
哦......
Oh...
右 左
Right, left.
我们不是第一个好心办坏事的人
We are not the first who with best meaning have incurred the worst!
我们不能见见女儿和姐姐么
Shall we not see these daughters and these sisters?
不 不 不 不
No, no, no, no.
过来 我们去监狱吧
Come, let's away to prison.
哈......
Ha...
我们俩会像笼中鸟一样歌唱
We two alone will sing like birds in the cage.
如果你需要我的祝福
When thou dost ask me blessing,
我会下跪乞求你的宽恕
I'll kneel down and ask of thee forgiveness.
我们会活着并祈祷 歌唱 讲故事
And so we'll live, and pray, and sing, and tell old tales,
我们会笑蝴蝶镀金
and laugh at gilded butterflies.
听可怜虫闲话宫廷轶事 我们也会同他们交谈
And hear poor rogues talk of court news and we'll talk with them too,
谁失 谁得 谁掌权 谁垮台
who loses and who wins, who's in, who's out...
我们能参透事态的秘密
and take upon us the mystery of things
我们是上帝派来的密探
as if we were God's spies.
我们会在这铜墙铁壁中冷眼旁观你们这群大人物
And we'll wear out in a walled prison packs and sects of great ones
随月圆月缺而浮沉
that ebb and flow by the moon.
对于这样的祭物 我的考狄利娅
Upon such sacrifices, my Cordelia,
天神也会焚香致敬
the gods themselves throw incense.
哈 我果然捉到你了么
Hm! Have I caught thee?
他要是想分开我们 必须从天上取来火把
He that parts us shall bring a brand from heaven,
像驱逐狐狸那样焚烧我们
and fire us hence like foxes.
擦干眼泪
Wipe thine eyes.
让恶疮吞噬掉他们的血肉
The good years shall devour them, flesh and fell
他们不能使我们落泪
ere they shall make us weep.
我们要先看着他们活活饿死
We'll see 'em starved first.
来
Come.
我把你提了一级
One step I have advanced thee.
要是你按照这张密令上的话去做 一定大有好处
If thou dost as this instructs thee, thou dost make thy way to noble fortunes.
愿意就做 不愿意就另谋出路吧
Either say thou'lt do it or thrive by other means.
我不会拖车子 也不会吃干麦
I cannot draw a cart nor eat dried oats.
只要是男子汉做的事 我都会去做
If it be man's work, I'll do it.
伯爵 您今天果然表明了您是一个将门之子 命运眷顾着您
Sir, you have showed today your valiant strain, and fortune led you well.
您的功劳重大 跟我们敌对的人都已束手就擒
You have the captives who were the opposites of this day's strife.
请您把俘虏交给我们
I do require them of you
我们会顾及到他们的身份和我们自身的安全而妥善安置他们
so that we shall find their merits and our safety may equally determine.
殿下 我已经把那个不幸的老国王拘禁起来了
Sir, I thought it fit to send the old and miserable king to some retention.
现在我们流血流汗
At this time we sweat and bleed.
折损了不少亲人朋友
The friend hath lost his friend,
他们不免心中激愤
and the best quarrels in the heat
见证过战争残酷的人们怨恨这场战争
are cursed by those that feel their sharpness.
对于考狄利娅和他父亲的审判应该选择一个更合适的时机
The question of Cordelia and her father requires a fitter place.
伯爵 说句不好听的 你只是个随征将领 并不是我的兄弟
Sir, by your patience, I hold you but a subject of this war, not as a brother.
他带领我们的军队 受到我的全权委托
He led our powers, bore the commission of my place and person,
就凭这层亲密的关系 就足够与你称兄道弟了
the which immediacy may well stand up and call itself your brother.
你可少亲热点
Not so hot.
他是靠着自己才能又不是靠着你的恩惠
In his own grace he doth exalt himself more than in your addition.
我把我的权利赋予他 他就能和最尊贵的人匹敌
In my rights by me invested, he compeers the best.
要是他是你丈夫 最多也不过如此吧
That were the most if he should husband you.
笑话往往会变成预言
Jesters do oft prove prophets.
呵呵 看你挤眉弄眼的果然不大对劲
Uh-uh. That eye that told you so looked but asquint.
姐姐 我不舒服
Lady, I am not well,
懒得跟你吵
else I should answer from a full-flowing stomach.
将军......
General...
请接受我的军队 俘虏 和财产
Take thou my soldiers, prisoners, patrimony.
包括我 都随你支配 这座城都是你的
Dispose of them, of me. These walls are thine.
让全世界为我证明 我要把你立为我的丈夫和君主
Witness the world that I create thee here my lord and master.
那不是你能阻止的
The let-alone lies not in your good will.
这与你无关
Nor in thine, lord.
杂种 跟我有关
Half-blooded fellow, yes.
证明下我把尊位让给了你
Prove my title thine.
埃德蒙 我有权以叛国罪和剥夺财产罪逮捕你
Edmund, I arrest thee on capital treason, and in thy attaint this gilded serpent.
这个插曲可真有意思
An interlude.
公开发出挑战
Let the challenge sound.
要是没有人出来指证 你所犯的无数凶残罪恶
If none appear to prove upon thy person thy heinous, manifest and many treasons,
-我以命相争
here is my pledge. I'll make it on my heart.
-我也愿赌上性命
There's my exchange.
谁骂我是叛徒
What in the world he is that names me traitor,
他就是一个说谎的恶人
villain-like he lies.
谁有胆量出来 我可以向他 向你 向每一个人
He that dares approach, on him, on you, who not?
证明我的不可动摇的忠心和荣誉
I will maintain my truth and honour firmly.
那就发出挑战吧
-Let the challenge sound.
哎哟 我感觉很不舒服
My sickness grows upon me.
她病了 把她扶到房间休息
She is not well, convey her to my room.
在本军之中 如有身份高贵的将校官佐
If any man of quality or degree within the lists of the army
愿意证明埃德蒙 未定名份的葛罗斯特伯爵
will maintain upon Edmund, supposed Earl of Gloucester,
是一个罪恶多端的叛徒
that he is a manifold traitor,
站出来
let him appear!
谁指使你来的
What sayest thou?
我宣布你是一个叛徒
Thou art a traitor,
你背叛了众神 背叛了你的哥哥和父亲
false to thy gods, thy brother, and thy father.
我要把这些罪名丢回到你头上
Back do I toss these treasons to thy head.
来吧
Yeah! Come on!
加油
-Fight! -
起来 起来
-Get up! -Get up.
你不是被人打败 你是中计了
Thou art not vanquished but cozened and beguiled!
闭嘴 你个妇人
Shut your mouth, dame!
不
No!
带她走 她绝望了
Go with her. She's desperate.
你指控我的罪状
What you have charged me with, that have I done.
而且 不止这些罪孽
And more, much more.
可你是谁
But what art thou?
在血统上 我并不比你低微 埃德蒙
I am no less in blood than thou art, Edmund.
我是埃德加
My name is Edgar...
你父亲的儿子
and thy father's son.
天道的车轮已经循环过来了
The wheel is come full circle.
我回来了
I am here.
我的心要爆裂了
O that my heart would burst...
救命 救命
Help! Help!
说吧  什么事
Well, speak, man.
这把刀
This knife...
这把刀是从心上拔下来的
This knife came even from the heart of...
谁的心 快说
Well, who, man? Speak!
你夫人
Your lady, sir.
你的夫人 把她的妹妹也给毒死了
Your lady. And her sister by her is poisoned.
她承认了
She confesses it.
尸体抬出来
Produce the bodies.
不管是死是活
Be they alive or dead.
快去
Go on.
我跟她们两人都有婚姻之约
I was contracted to them both.
现在我们三个人可以一起做夫妻了
All three now marry in an instant.
我要来上我的国王道一声永久的晚安
I am come to bid my king and master aye good night.
他不在这儿吗
Is he not here?
你见过这种场景吗 肯特
Seest thou this object, Kent?
我快要断气了
I pant for life.
快差人阻止
Quickly send...
我下令要处死李尔和科迪莉亚
for my writ is on the life of Lear and on Cordelia.
快去阻止
Send in time!
-差一点就来不及了 -把他抬下去
-Haste thee for thy life! -Bear him hence!
哀号吧
Howl!
你们这些石头一样的人
O you are men of stones.
要是我有了你们的那些舌头和眼睛 我要用我的眼泪和哭声震撼苍穹
Had I your tongues and eyes, I'd use them so that heaven's vault should crack.
她已经去世了
She's gone... for ever.
一个人死了还是活着 我是知道的
I know when one is dead and when one lives.
她已经向泥土一样死去
She's dead as earth.
这根羽毛在动
This feather stirs.
她就还活着
She lives.
要是她还有命活
If it be so, it is a chance
那我的一切悲哀 都可以消逝了
which does redeem all sorrows that ever I have felt.
-我的好主人
O my good master...
走开
Prithee, away.
这是尊贵的肯特 您的朋友
'Tis noble Kent, your friend.
一场瘟疫降落在你们身上 你们全是凶手 奸贼
A plague upon us, murderers, traitors all!
我本可以把她救活的
I might have saved her.
而她再也
Now she's gone...
回不来了
for ever.
科迪莉亚
Cordelia...
科迪莉亚 等一等
Cordelia, stay a little. Ha?
你说什么
What is't thou sayest?
她的声音总是那么柔软温和
Her voice was ever soft, gentle and low.
女儿家是应该这样的
An excellent thing in woman.
我亲手杀死了把你缢死的奴才
I killed the slave that was a-hanging thee.
我不是把他杀死了吗
Did I not, fellow?
是的 大人
'Tis true, my lords, he did.
从前 我一举起我的宝刀 就可以把他们吓得抱头鼠窜
I have seen the day, with my good biting falchion I'd have made 'em skip!
现在我老了
I'm old now,
收到这许多磨难
and these same crosses spoil me.
一天不如一天
This is a dull sight.
你是谁
Who are you?
我跟你说 我的眼睛可不太好
Mine eyes are not of the best, I'll tell you straight.
你是肯特吗
Are you not Kent?
陛下 正是您的仆人 肯特
The same, your servant Kent.
你的随从卡厄斯呢
Where is your servant, Caius?
我可以告诉你 他是一个好人
He's a good man, I'll tell you that.
他一动起火来就打人 -他已经死的骨头都腐烂了
He'll strike, and quickly too. He's dead and rotten.
不 陛下
No, my good lord!
-我就是那个人 -我马上就能认出来你不是
-I am the very man... -I'll see that straight.
那个从您开始遭遇变故以来 就一直跟随着您的人
...that from your first of difference and decay have followed your sad steps.
欢迎 欢迎
You are welcome hither.
他不知道自己在说什么 我们谒见他也是徒劳的
He knows not what he says and vain is it that we present us to him.
大人 尊贵的朋友 听我说
My lords and noble friends, know our intent.
我们要尽量给他可能的安慰
What comfort to this great decay may come shall be applied.
当他在世的时候 我仍旧
For us, we will resign
把最高的权利归还给他
during the life of this old majesty to him our absolute power.
哦 快看啊
O see, see!
还有 我可怜的傻女儿也缢死了
And... and my poor fool... is hanged.
不 不
No... No...
没有命了
No life.
为什么一条狗 一匹马 一只耗子都有生命
Why should a dog, a horse, a rat have life...
你却没有一丝呼吸
and thou no breath at all?
你是永远回不来了
Thou'lt come no more.
永不
Never...
永不 永不 永不
Never, never, never...
请你替我解开这个纽扣
Pray you, undo this button.
谢谢你先生
Thank you, sir.
瞧瞧
See this?
瞧瞧她
Look...
她的嘴唇
On her, her lips.
看那儿 看那儿
Look there, look there.
他晕过去了
- -He faints.
陛下
My lord...
My lord?
碎吧 心啊 碎吧
Oh. Break, heart, I prithee break.
抬起头来 陛下
Look up, my lord.
不要烦扰他的灵魂 啊 让他安然死去吧
O, vex not his ghost. O, let him pass.
他将要痛恨那些想要使他在这无情世上
He hates him that would upon the rack of this tough world stretch him out longer.
他真的去了
He is gone indeed.
他居然忍受了这么久的时候
The wonder is he hath endured so long.
他的生命不是他自己的
He but usurped his life.
两位朋友
Friends of my soul,
请帮我主持大政重振国本
you twain rule in this realm and the gor'd state sustain.
不日间我将登程上道
I have a journey, sir, shortly to go.
我听到了主上的召唤 使命所在
My master calls me. I must not say no.
不幸的重担不能不肩负
The weight of this sad time we must obey,
感情是我们唯一的语言
speak what we feel, not what we ought to say.
年老的人已经忍受了一切
The oldest hath borne most.
后人只有 抚陈迹
We that are young shall never see so much,
而叹息
nor live so long.
有高清电影网出品
yougaoqing.com
新浪微博 @摆渡字幕组 译制